<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy, and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs with Queen Elizabeth's admonition, declaring the sence and interpretation of it, confirmed by an act of Parliament, in the 5th year of her reign : together with a vindication of dissenters, proving, that their particular congregations are not inconsistent with the King's supremacy in ecclesiastical affairs : with some account of the nature, constitution, and power of the ecclesiastical courts / by P. Nye ... ; in the epistle to the reader is inserted King James's vindication and explication of the oath of allegiance.</title>
            <title>Lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs</title>
            <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22153</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12570075</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12570075</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 747:3 or 770:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy, and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs with Queen Elizabeth's admonition, declaring the sence and interpretation of it, confirmed by an act of Parliament, in the 5th year of her reign : together with a vindication of dissenters, proving, that their particular congregations are not inconsistent with the King's supremacy in ecclesiastical affairs : with some account of the nature, constitution, and power of the ecclesiastical courts / by P. Nye ... ; in the epistle to the reader is inserted King James's vindication and explication of the oath of allegiance.</title>
                  <title>Lawfulnes of the oath of supremacy and power of the King in ecclesiastical affairs</title>
                  <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ..., and Samuel Crowch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Verso of A1 has the Oath of allegiance.</note>
                  <note>Published in 1687 with title: The King's authority in dispensing with ecclesiastical laws, asserted and vindicated.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at 747:3 incorrectly called N1496 in reel guide.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:1"/>
            <head>The Oath of Allegiance.</head>
            <p>I <hi>A B</hi> do truly and ſincerely acknowledg, profeſs, teſtify and declare in my Conſcience, before God and the VVorld, that our Sovereign Lord; KING <hi>CHARLES</hi> is Lawful and Rightful KING of this Realm, and of all other his Majeſty's Dominions and Countries, And that the Pope, neither of himſelf, nor by any Authority of the Church or See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means, with any other, hath any Power or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to Depoſe the KING, or to diſpoſe any of his Majeſty's Kingdoms or Dominions, or to Authorize any Foreign Prince to invade or annoy Him or his Countries; or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge any of his Subjects of their Allegiance or Obedience to his Majeſty; or to give Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe or Leave to any of them to bear Arms, to raiſe Tumults, to offer any Violence or Hurt to his Majeſty's Royal Perſon, State, or Government, or to any of his Majeſty's Subjects within his Majeſty's Dominions. Alſo I do ſwear from my Heart, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Declaration, or Sentence of Excommunication, or Deprivation, made or granted, or to be made and granted by the Pope, or his Succeſſors, or by any Authority de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, or pretended to be derived from him, or his See, againſt the ſaid King, his Heirs or Succeſſors, or any Abſolution of the ſaid Subjects from their Obedience; I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my Power, againſt all Conſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crown or Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration, or otherwiſe; and will do my beſt endeavour to diſcloſe and make known unto his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, all Treaſons, and Traiterous Conſpiracies, which I ſhall know or hear of, to be againſt him or any of them. And I further ſwear, That I do from my Heart abhor, deteſt and abjure, as Impious and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, this damnable Doctrine and Poſition, That Princes which be Excommunicated or Deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their Subjects, or any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And I do believe, and in my Conſcience am reſolved, that neither the Pope, nor any other Perſon whatſoever, hath Power to abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof, which I acknowledg by good full Authority to be Lawfully miniſtred unto me; and do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all Pardons and Diſpenſations to the contrary. And all theſe Things I do plainly and ſincerely acknowledg and ſwear, according to theſe expreſs VVords by me ſpoken, and according to the Plain and Common Sence and Underſtanding of the ſame VVords, without any Equivocation, or Mental Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation whatſoever. And I do make this Recognition and Acknowledgment heartily, willingly and truly, upon the true Faith of a Chriſtian. <hi>So help me God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi> you may ſee at large in this Book, <hi>page</hi> 2.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAWFULNES OF THE <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> AND Power of the King IN Eccleſiaſtical Affairs.</p>
            <p>With Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s ADMONITION, declaring the Sence and Interpretation of it, confirmed by an Act of Parliament, in the <hi>5th</hi> Year of her Reign.</p>
            <p>Together with a Vindication of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> proving, That their particular Congregations are not inconſiſtent with the King's Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs.</p>
            <p>With ſome Account of the Nature, Conſtitution, and Power of the <hi>ECCLESIASTICAL CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RTS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>P. NYE,</hi> a Congregational Divine, ſometime Miniſter in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the Reader is inſerted King <hi>James</hi>'s Vindication and Explication of the Oath of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, and <hi>Samuel Crowch</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE reprinting of this judicious and learned Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Mr.</hi> Nye<hi>'s, is occaſioned by the re-impoſing of the Oaths of</hi> Allegiance <hi>and</hi> Supremacy <hi>on the City of</hi> London <hi>at this Juncture for Election of Common-Councel-Men; ſome ſuppoſing that many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters will refuſe the ſaid Oaths, or at leaſt that of the</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, <hi>but by what is here ſaid it will appear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King <hi>James</hi> in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>'s Lies, ſaith, The <hi>Puritans</hi> do not decline the Oath of <hi>Supremacys,</hi> but do daily take it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the ſame <hi>Supremacy</hi> is defended by <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Inſtit.</hi> l. 4. c 20. Bp <hi>Andrews</hi> ſays the ſame, <hi>Tortura Torti,</hi> p. 110.</note> 
               <hi>that the Principles of Diſſenters are not inconſiſtent with the King's Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, and as a further Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony hereof, as they have* formerly, ſo they are again ready to take the ſaid Oaths, and profeſſedly aſſent alſo to all the Articles of Religion, which concern only the Confeſſion of the true Christian Faith, and the Doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, compriſed in a Book, entituled,</hi> Articles, &amp;c. <hi>print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> 1562, <hi>and ſo do humbly hope, living peaceably under his Majeſties Government, they ſhall obtain that Indulgence which his Majeſty hath often graciouſly promiſed, and which they formerly enjoyed, his Majeſty having told us in his Declaration for Indulgence,</hi> — It being evident by the ſad Experience of twelve years, that there is little fruit of forcible courſes. <hi>And in his gracious Speech,</hi> Febr. 5. 1672, <hi>aſſured the Parliament that he had</hi> hitherto found the good Effect of the ſaid Indulgence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reverend Author hath ſaid nothing of the Oath of</hi> Allegiance, <hi>ſuppoſing no</hi> Proteſtant <hi>ſcruples that (unleſs it be ſuch as ſcruple all manner of Swearing:) but that all may underſtand the nature and deſign of both, I will here inſert the Words of King</hi> James, <hi>in his Apologie for the Oath of Allegiance, p.</hi> 46, <hi>&amp;c. in his Anſwer to Card.</hi> Bellarmin<hi>'s Letters, Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:3"/>
            <p>As the Oath of Supremacy was deviſed for putting a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Papiſts, and them of our Profeſſion; ſo was this Oath [of Allegiance] which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would ſeem to impugn, ordained for making the Difference between the civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obedent Papiſts, and the perverſe Diſciples of the Powder-Treaſon. In King <hi>Henry</hi> Eighth's time was the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy firſt made; by him were <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> and <hi>Roffenſis</hi> put to death, partly for refuſing it. From his time till now, have all the Princes of this Land, profeſſing this Religion, ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in effect, maintained the ſame: and in that Oath only is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the King's Abſolute Power to be Judge over all Perſons, as well Civil as Eccleſiaſtical; excluding all Foreign Powers and Potentates to be Judges within his Dominions: Whereas this laſt made Oath containeth no ſuch matter, only medling with the Civil Obedience of Subjects to their Sovereign in meer Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Cauſes. And that the Injuſtice as well as the Error of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi>'s groſs miſtaking in this Point, may yet be more clearly diſcovered; I have alſo thought good to inſert here immediately after the Oath of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> the contrary Concluſions to all the Points and Articles, whereof this other late Oath doth conſiſt; whereby it may appear what unreaſonable and rebellious Points he would drive my Subjects unto, by refuſing the whole Body or that Oath, as it is conceived. For he that ſhall refuſe to take this Oath, muſt of neceſſity hold all or ſome of theſe Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That I King <hi>James</hi> am not the lawful King of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of all other my Dominions.</item>
               <item>2. That the Pope by his own Authority many depoſe me: If not by his own Authority, yet by ſome other Authority of the Church, or of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> If not by ſome other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church and See of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet by other means with others help he may depoſe me.</item>
               <item>3. That the Pope may diſpoſe of my Kingdoms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</item>
               <item>4. That the Pope may give Authority to ſome Foreign Prince to invade my Dominions.</item>
               <item>5. That the Pope may diſcharge my Subjects of their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Allegiance to me.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:63430:3"/>
               <item>6. That the Pope may give Licence to one or more of my Subjects to bear Arms againſt me.</item>
               <item>7. That the Pope may give leave to my Subjects to offer Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to my Perſon, or to my Government, or to ſome of my Subjects.</item>
               <item>8. That if the Pope ſhall by Sentence excommunicate or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me, my Subjects are not to bear Faith and Allegiance to me.</item>
               <item>9. If the Pope ſhall by Sentence excommunicate or depoſe me, my Subjects are not bound to defend with all their power my Perſon and Crown.</item>
               <item>10. If the Pope ſhall give out any Sentence of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or Deprivation againſt me, my Subjects by reaſon of that Sentence, are not bound to reveal all Conſpiracies and Treaſons againſt me, which ſhall come to their Hearing and Knowledg.</item>
               <item>11. That it is not heretical and deteſtable to hold that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being excommunicated by the Pope, may be either depoſed or killed by their Subjects, or any other.</item>
               <item>12. That the Pope hath Power to abſolve my Subjects from this Oath, or from ſome par thereof.</item>
               <item>13. That this Oath is not adminiſtred to my Subjects, by a full and lawful Authority.</item>
               <item>14. That this Oath is to be taken with Equivocation, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Evaſion, or ſecret Reſervation; and not with the Heart and good Will ſincerely, in the Faith of a Chriſtian Man.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are the true and natural Branches of the Body of this Oath.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:4"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>THe Occaſion of this Oath, various Form and Alteration of it. Interpretations of this Oath given in our Laws, and Writers of note. The nature of our Aſſent and Stipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>What is ment by Things and Perſons Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical, in the proper as alſo in the vulgar uſe of theſe Terms.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Of Power, its riſe and original. Two ſorts of Power in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical or Spiritual Things, their Agreement and Difference.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Of the neceſſity and uſefulneſs of a Juriſdiction over Perſons and in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, beſides what is in Churches and Church-men. This Power is placed in Kings, and ſuch as are the ſupream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in a Common-wealth.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>The Government of particular Churches hath Affinity with Families, Cities, and the like leſſer Bodies, more than with the Government of Empires and Kingdoms, confirmed in ſix Inſtances.</item>
                     <item>A Digreſſion. Of Independency Name and Thing; its conſiſtency with the King's Supreamacy.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Of the Juriſdiction over particular Churches, placed in Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, as it is.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Exerciſed with us in this Nation.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> As it is in other Reformed Churches, herein;</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of Appeals that are properly ſuch in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, theſe are always to be to the Supream Civil Magiſtrate only, or to ſuch as are appointed by him.</item>
                     <item>A Poſt-ſcript, giving ſome account of the congregational way from ſuch Principles of it, as are laid down in this Treatiſ.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63430:4"/>
            <head>THE LAWFULNES OF THE Oath of Supremacy, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Supremacy of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eclipſed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in both parts of it, the State thought fit to enjoin a Proviſion of equal extenſion. In relation to the <hi>Civil Rights</hi> of the Crown, is the Oath of <hi>Allegiance;</hi> and againſt the Encroachments upon the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> this of the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which being firſt enjoined, containeth in a manner both. This Oath hath given the Papiſts ſuch a Blow, as they could not but ſtrike again, and have poured out a Flood of Arguments and Abſurdities againſt ſubmitting to it, which hath been a long time ſcattered, and ſtick in the Minds of divers of his Majeſty's Loyal Subjects; who, tho otherwiſe well affected, yet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome Doubts and Tenderneſs, are at a ſtand to this day, and ſcruple the taking of this Oath: For whoſe ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and clearing the Lawfulneſs of this Supremacy, is the enſuing D. ſcourſe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:63430:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>§. <hi>1.</hi> The Oath it ſelf, as now enjoined. §. <hi>2.</hi> The Occaſion of this Oath. §. <hi>3.</hi> Various Forms of it, and Alterations about it. §. <hi>4.</hi> Interpretations given of it in our Laws, and Writers of Note. §. <hi>5.</hi> The Nature of our Aſſent and Stipulation.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oath">
                              <head>The Oath of <hi>Supremacy.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>I A. B.</hi> do utterly teſtify and declare in my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the King's Highneſs is the only Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governor of this Realm, and of all other his Highneſs's Dominions and Countries, as well in all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Things or Cauſes, as Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral: And that no Foreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath, or ought to have any Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, Power, Superiority, Preeminence, or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, within this Realm. And therefore I do utterly renounce and forſake all Foreign Iurisdictions, Powers, Superiorities, and Authorities, and do promiſe, that from henceforth I ſhall bear Faith and true Allegiance to the King's Highneſs, his Heirs and lawful Succeſſors; and to my power ſhall asſiſt and defend all Iurisdictions, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, Preeminences, and Authorities, granted or belonging to the King's Highneſs, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, as united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:63430:5"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 2. For many Years there hath been a Conteſt about Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Supremacy in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters, between the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> who hath got ground herein, according as our Princes were found more weak, neceſſitous, or devoted to his Holineſs. <hi>Rome</hi> was not built in a Day. By <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>Legates</hi> from the Pope, to hear and determine Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, were admitted. <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt, after much Conteſt, yields to the Pope the Patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Donations of Biſhopricks, and all other Eccleſiaſtical Benefices; it being decreed at <hi>Rome,</hi> that no Lay-Perſon ſhould give any Eccleſiaſtical Charge. King <hi>Stephen</hi> grants, that <hi>Appeals</hi> be made to the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> In <hi>Henry</hi> the Second's Days, the Pope gets the Clergy, and Spiritual Perſons, exempted from Secular Powers. The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is now over all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons and Cauſes, even in theſe Dominions, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head. And having upon the matter made Conqueſt over more than half the Kingdom, in the Times of King <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, ſets on for the whole, and obtains of King <hi>John</hi> an abſolute Surrender of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> unto his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which were granted back again by him to the King, to hold of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in Fee-farm and Vaſſalage. Being now abſolute and immediate Lord over all, he endeavours to convert the Profits of both Kingdoms to his own Uſe; ſo that <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> were hereby reduced to very great Poverty and Servitude.</p>
                  <p>Such Ruine being brought upon both Kingdoms by this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Engine, (the Claim and Exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over Perſons and Cauſes by a Foreign Power) the Nation was awakened, both <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> yea, the <hi>Spiritual Lords</hi> themſelves, to join with more Vigor againſt this Foreign Uſurpation. To this purpoſe ſevere Laws were made, in the Time of <hi>Edw. 1ſt, 2d, 3d. Richard</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> Notwithſtanding theſe Laws, (and ſome formerly, as the Conſtitutions of <hi>Clarendon</hi> by <hi>Hen.</hi> 2.) partly by Sufferance, and partly by Negligence, the whole Nation being Catholick, and held under a devotional Slavery, there was no thorow or ſucceſsful Conteſt againſt theſe Oppreſſions. They remained unto, and were complained of in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Days; as of <hi>Appeals to</hi> Rome <hi>in Cauſes of Matrimony, Divorce, Tithes,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63430:6"/>
                     <hi>to the great Inquietation, Vexation and Trouble, Coſts and Charges of the King's Highneſs, and many of his Subjects.</hi> 24 Hen. 8. cap. 12. In a further Complaint, <hi>Anno</hi> 25, cap. 21. it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, how that <hi>the Subjects of this Realm have been greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay'd and impoveriſhed by intolerable Exactions of great Sums of Money, claimed, and taken out of this Realm by the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>as well in Penſions, Cenſes, Peter-Pence, Procurations, Proviſions, Delegacies, Reſcripts in Cauſes of Contention and Appeals, as alſo for Diſpenſations, Licenſes, Faculties,</hi> &amp;c. who aſſumed a Power to diſpenſe with all humane <hi>Laws, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes, and Cuſtoms of all Realms.</hi> And many the like Complaints were made to King <hi>Henry,</hi> by his Parliament, at ſeveral times, as it appears in the Statutes of that Age: In which Statutes, as in that of the <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. &amp; 25. <hi>c.</hi> 21.26. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 3. <hi>Anno</hi> 28. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 7, 10, 16, and 35 <hi>c.</hi> 1. you have the whole Fabrick of Romiſh Uſurpation laid level, and all Eccleſiaſtical Power reduced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Majeſty's Dominions, and placed in the Arch Biſhop, and other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons under him, by firm and ſevere Laws.</p>
                  <p>This being done, the King is petitioned by his Lords and Commons, <hi>That for further Corroboration of thoſe Acts, and utterly to exclude the long uſurped Power, Authority, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>that an OATH, containing the Subſtance and Effect of thoſe Statutes, be limited and tendred to his Subjects.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Parcel of Sacred Worſhip (an Oath) is indulged to Mankind in Civil Affairs. Such is the Falſeneſs, Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Uncertainty of Men, as that human Societies could hardly ſubſiſt without it. The Lord, to repair our Credit, hath formed Mens Hearts generally to a great and apparent Religion, and Reverence of this Ordinance. The Heathens themſelves termed it <hi>Sacramium,</hi> as if the moſt eminent or only Thing Sacred, and religiouſly to be obſerved. It is ſo effectual a Means to eſtabliſh a Reformation, as <hi>Men will be kept firm by Oaths,</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>tho there were neither Laws nor Magiſtrates.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Liv. Hiſt.</note> We are expoſed to more Variety and Changes from <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſteadineſs in the Mind,</hi> than from any thing that is <hi>without us.</hi> Fix the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and you ſix the Man, whatever Evil he is thereby expoſed to. There is nothing generally more effectual to fix the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience than an Oath: If I have ſworn, and invocated the Name of God in an Engagement, it will be an <hi>End of all Strife,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63430:6"/>diſpute with my ſelf, as well as with others, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Reſolutions are in common apprehenſion become immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, when <hi>confirmed by an Oath,</hi> ver. 17.<note place="margin">Numb. 30.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>ſweareth an Oath, and bindeth his Soul by a Bond.</hi> It is the Bond of the Soul, we have given Security for our Faithfulneſs from Heaven. For removing the Romiſh Yoke, which lay ſo heavy upon Prince and People, Means hath been uſed again and again, almoſt in each King's Reign, for near Four Hundred Years but to no great effect. Goſpel-Light dawning about us, and the binding of our Souls by an Oath, hath been the fixing of this great Work, and the beſt Fence againſt Popery that ever was ſet up. I have ſpoken the more ſully of the <hi>Occaſion,</hi> and this <hi>Means</hi> (our Oath), that we may not judg the taking of it to be a <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Name of God in vain;</hi> for as long as this Nation is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Popiſh Tyranny in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, ſo long is this Oath of abſolute uſe and advantage, as the beſt Security between Man and Man for Union againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 3. A Parliament being called in 22 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the King was recognized by the Clergy of that Convocation, <hi>Supreme Head of the Church;</hi> the Expreſſion or Form hereof debated, a reed upon, and ſubſcribed by each Perſon there, was this: <hi>Cujus (Eccleſiae Anglicanae) ſingularem Protectorem, unicum &amp; ſupremum Dominum, &amp; (quantum per Chriſti leges liect) ſupremum Caput, ipſius Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem recognoſcimus.</hi> This Title was afterwards confirmed by divers Acts of Parliament, and two Oaths formed to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in one Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> 28 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the one more brief, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with it the Succeſſion of the Crown, in <hi>cap.</hi> 7. the other more full and large, and to this purpoſe only, <hi>cap.</hi> 10. Some Years after, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>An.</hi> 35 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. a Revive of both theſe Oaths was made by the Parliament, and with ſome Alterations reduced into one: The Reaſons there are given why this was done; and it was reſolved, <hi>Thoſe Oaths ſhall not therefore be adminiſtred, and this Oath to ſtand in force and place of the two Oaths.</hi> Which Oath began thus:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oath">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>having now the Vail of Darkneſs of the uſurped Power of the See and Biſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>clearly taken away from mine Eyes, do utterly teſtify,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63430:7"/>
                  <p>This Oath remained the ſame the reſt of his Reign, and all <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time. Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in the firſt Year of her Reign, made theſe Alterations: 1. That Expreſſion of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head,</hi> &amp;c. went hardly down by ſome, as taking too much from the Pope; and as giving too much to any Secular Prince, by others. Tho <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> by his Letter written to the Clergy of <hi>York</hi>-Province,<note place="margin">Anno <hi>1533.</hi>
                     </note> well defends it; yet Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by her Parliament changed that Expreſſion.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>The Oath was alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> (to uſe Secretary <hi>Walſingham</hi>'s Words) <hi>into a more grateful Form,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In his Letter to <hi>Critoy,</hi> Sec. of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the hardneſs of the Name, and the Appellation of</hi> Supreme Head <hi>being removed.</hi> 2. This Oath by that 35 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. might be tendered to any Subject at the King's pleaſure, <hi>cap.</hi> 1. By the Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 8. the urging of it was limited to certain Perſons, employed in Publick Truſt. 3. The Penalty for refuſing it, at firſt was no leſs than High-Treaſon: By the Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Puniſhment for Refuſal is only a Diſenablement to take any Promotion, or exerciſe any Publick Charge, yet with this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo,</hi> if afterwards during Life there were a ſubmitting to take this Oath, the Perſon might be reſtored to his Office or Charge. But by the Parliament in 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Puniſhment (which as yet ſtands) is greater: The firſt Refuſal of the Oath brings the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within a <hi>Praemunire;</hi> and if tendred a ſecond time, after the ſpace of three Months, and again refuſed by the ſame Perſon, it is High-Treaſon. This Severity in the Puniſhment, is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with a more gentle and indulgent Interpretation of the Oath, as will appear in the following <hi>Section.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As we are not to ſwear raſhly, ſo our Laws do not give Oaths raſhly, but with great care and tenderneſs, weighing and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering both the Matter, Perſons, Penalties, and the Seaſon or Occaſion, being not willing their Laws, or Puniſhments for breaking of them, be a Snare, or at any time more grievous to the Subject than the Neceſſity of State requires.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 4. The true Scope and Sence of this Oath may be gathered from the Laws and Statutes ſince eſtabliſhed, and ſome Light alſo from other Writers of Note.</p>
                  <p>Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> within a little time after this Oath was reduced to the Form wherein now it ſtands, in an <hi>Admonition</hi> annexed to the <hi>Injunctions,</hi> declareth the Sence and Interpretation of it, as followeth.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63430:7"/>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="text">
                              <head>The Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion annexed to the Queen's Injunctions.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>THe Queen's Majeſty being informed, that in certain Places of this Realm, ſundry of her Native Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects being called to Eccleſiaſtical Miniſtry in the Church, be, by ſiniſter Perſuaſion, and perverſe Conſtruction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to find ſome ſcruple in the Form of an Oath, which by an Act of the laſt Parliament is preſcribed to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of divers Perſons, for the Recognition of their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to her Majeſty, which certainly neither was ever</hi> meant, <hi>ne by any</hi> equity of Words, <hi>or</hi> good Sence, <hi>can be thereof gathered; would that all her Loving Subjects ſhould underſtand, that nothing was, is, or ſhall be meant or intended by the ſame Oath, to have any other Duty, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, or Bond required by the ſame Oath, than was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be due to the moſt noble Kings of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, her Majeſty's Father, or King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth, her Majeſty's Brother.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>And further, her Majeſty forbiddeth all manner her Subjects to give ear or credit to ſuch perverſe and malicious Perſons, which moſt ſiniſterly and maliciouſly labour to noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy to her Loving Subjects, how by the Words of the ſaid Oath it may be collected, the Kings or Queens of this Realm, Poſſeſſors of the Crown, may challenge</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Power of Miniſtry <hi>of Divine Offices in the Church; wherein her ſaid Subjects be much abuſed by ſuch evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Perſons: For certainly her Majeſty neither doth, ne ever will challenge any other Authority, than that was challenged, and lately uſed by the ſaid noble Kings of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memory, King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>the Sixth, which is, and was of ancient time</hi> due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm: <hi>That is, under God, to have the Sovereignty and Rule over all manner of Perſons</hi> born within theſe her Realms, <hi>Dominions, and Countries, of what Eſtate, either Eccleſiaſtical or Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſoever they be, ſo as no other Foreign Power ſhall, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63430:8"/>ought to have any Superiority over them. And if any Perſon, that hath conceived any other Sence of the Form of the ſaid Oath, ſhall accept the ſame Oath with this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, Sence, or Meaning, her Majeſty is well pleaſed to accept every ſuch in that behalf, as her good and obedient Subjects, and ſhall acquit them of all manner Penalties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhall peremptorily or obſtinately refuſe to take the ſame Oath.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>In the fifth Year of her Reign, there is by Act of Parliament, a Confirmation of this Sence, by way of <hi>Proviſo,</hi> in theſe Words:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="proviso">
                              <head>The <hi>Proviſo</hi> in the Statute of 5 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Provided alſo, That the Oath expreſſed in the ſaid Act, made in the ſaid firſt Year, ſhall be taken and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in ſuch Form as is ſet forth in an Admonition annexed to the Queen's Majeſty's Injunctions, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the firſt Year of her Majeſties Reign: That is to ſay, to confeſs and acknowledg in her Majeſty, her Heirs and Succeſſors, none other Authority than that was challenged, and lately uſed by the Noble King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, and King</hi> Edward <hi>the Sixth, as in the ſaid Admonition more plainly may appear.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>There may be a Doubt made about this Interpretation, as whether it be not inconſiſtent with the Words of the Oath, it ſeems to be rather a material Change of them, than an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation. In the Oath it is, <hi>All Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Things or Cauſes;</hi> in the Interpretation it is, <hi>All manner of Perſons, of what Eſtate, either Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal, ſoever they be.</hi> The Oath ſeems to ſpeak of one thing, and the Interpretation of another;<note place="margin">Ad leges, per ſe requiritur poteſtas in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmam, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio in res altas. <hi>Suarez</hi> de Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> the one of Cauſes, and the other of Perſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no oppoſition or Inconſiſtency between theſe two, <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Cauſes.</hi> The principal Object of a Law is a Perſon, and a Perſon with reſpect to his Actions, a Perſon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conſidered; for a Perſon phyſical, that is, in his Being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Nature as Man, without moving, or acting any thing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63430:8"/>good or evil, is not the Object of a Law: nor Actions of any kind or ſort whatſoever, as Actions, and in that general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, do come under a Law, but as they reſpect Perſons, and are ſome way or other the Actions of reaſonable Creatures: Tho a Law be made to puniſh the <hi>Ox which goreth a Man that he dieth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Fxod. 21.29.</note> yet it is with reſpect to Man, to let him know how much God is provoked by ſhedding Man's Blood, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Doth God care for Oxen?</hi> Doth God in his Law reſpect the Beaſt for it ſelf? is it not that Man may be inſtructed and reſtained? <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. <hi>He ſaith it altogether for our ſakes.</hi> The mentioning of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Cauſes therefore doth imply Perſons, and Perſons of the ſame Denomination, to whom ſuch Actions are peculiar, that is, Eccleſiaſtical Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And that this latter is an Interpretation of the former, will thus appear: The Oath, in giving a Supremacy in all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, might ſeem to imply Spiritual Things to be the immediate and proper Object of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Power, and ſpiritual Perſons, only for this, becauſe they had to do in ſpiritual Matters; and to infer thence, that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath Power in ſpiritual Adminiſtrations, as the Word and Sacraments, after the ſame manner as hath the Miniſters of Chriſt, who have Power in theſe Things, as the principal and immediate Object of their Function: Which this Form af Expreſſion in the Admonition doth clearly take away, 1. In aſſerting, that <hi>by the Words of the ſaid Oath, Kings or Queens of this Realm may not challenge Authority and Power of Miniſtry of Divine Offices in the Church.</hi> 2. The mentioning Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons, and not Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes at all, implieth, that the Perſons of Biſhops, Presbyters, and ſuch like, are primarily and immediately the Object of this Supreme Power, and the Laws made by it, upon another Conſideration than as Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> namely, as being <hi>born within theſe her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Realms and Dominions, and ſuch Perſons, of what Eſtate, either Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal, ſoever they be, She hath the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty and Rule over them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical Things are mentioned in the Oath upon a twofold Account: 1. Becauſe the Civil Magiſtrate's Power and Juriſdiction really extends it ſelf to the Duties of both Tables, and hath to do with Matters and Cauſes, as well as Perſons, that are ſpiritual, (as hereafter we ſhall ſhew)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63430:9"/>but, 2. Principally, that a Calling or Employment in Church-Affairs, (whatſoever hath been formerly judged and practiſed) doth no more exempt a Perſon and his Actings, (that is a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Queen upon any other account) from her Secular Power, than doth a Temporal Calling or Employment in any worldly Affairs.</p>
                  <p>There is ſomething of Explication further, in the Articles of Religion, concluded in the Year 1562. The <hi>37th</hi> Article is this:</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="article">
                              <head>The <hi>37th</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The Queen's Majeſty hath the chief Power in her Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and other her Dominions, unto whom the chief Government of all Eſtates of this Realm, whether they be Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, in all Cauſes doth appertain, and is not, nor ought to be ſubject to any Foreign Juriſdiction.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Where we attribute to the Queen's Majeſty the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by which Titles we underſtand the Minds of ſome ſlanderous Folks to be offended, we give not to our Prince the ministring either of God's Word, or of the Sacraments: The which thing the Injunctions alſo, lately ſet forth by</hi> Elizabeth <hi>our Queen, do most plainly testify: But that only Prerogative, which we ſee to have been given always to all Godly Princes in Holy Scriptures, by God himſelf; that is, that they ſhould rule all Eſtates and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees committed to their Charge by God, whether they be Eccleſiastical or Temporal, and restrain with the Civil Sword the Stubborn, and Evil-doers.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>hath no Juriſdiction in this Realm of</hi> England.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>It is mentioned in the <hi>Admonition,</hi> that the Queen's Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Power is <hi>the ſame that was challenged and uſed by</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth,</hi> &amp;c. Which is ſuppoſed by ſome, to be the ſame that was in the Pope, the <hi>Perſon</hi> only, and not the <hi>Power</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; ſo that our Princes are but Secular Popes. This Objection
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63430:9"/>was ſtrengthned by the Subtilty of <hi>Gardiner</hi> abroad;<note place="margin">Whom <hi>Calvin</hi> terms <hi>Impoſtor ille,</hi> in Am. 7.13.</note> and at home, by a Sermon preached at <hi>Paul</hi>'s-Croſs, in the Year 1588, by Dr. <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who calls Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> a <hi>petty Pope,</hi> and tells us, her Eccleſiaſtical Authority is the ſame which the Pope had formerly. This <hi>37th</hi> Article removes the Scruple ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently: 1. In aſſerting the Authority given to her Majeſty to be no other but what <hi>we ſee to have been given to all Godly Princes in holy Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. And for what Power <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth challenged, it was no new Juriſdiction wreſted from the Pope, but a Power or Prerogative <hi>juſtly and rightfully</hi> belonging to him,<note place="margin">26 <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> claimed and exerciſed by his Predeceſſors ſome hundreds of Years before his Time, being anciently annexed to the Crown. 2. In the latter part of the Article it is alſo evident: For tho a Power in ſpiritual Cauſes be given to a Secular Prince, yet it is not a <hi>ſpiritual Power,</hi> and ſuch a Juriſdiction as the Pope claims, but ſuch a Power only, and in ſuch a way as is put forth and exerciſed in ordinary Civil Affairs; and the ſame, in reſpect both to Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Perſons, namely, a <hi>reſtraining with the Civil Sword the Stubborn and Evil-doers.</hi> So to reſtrain or coerce, is an Authority or Juriſdiction peculiar to Civil Magiſtrates, and by Chriſt himſelf denied to the higheſt <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Powers.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 20, 25, 26.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye know</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Dominion over them; and they that are great, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Authority upon them: but it ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> you apoſtles; and threatens the Uſe of the Sword in ſuch <hi>Perſons, Mat.</hi> 26.52.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>James</hi> ſpeaking of the Oath of Supremacy; <q>In that Oath (ſaith he) is contained <hi>only</hi> the King's abſolute Power over all Perſons, as well Civil as Eccleſiaſtical, excluding all Foreign Powers and Potentates to be Judges within his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</q> In his <hi>Apol. pag.</hi> 76. And more fully afterwards, <hi>pag.</hi> 164. <q>It implies (ſaith he) a Power to command Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be given to the Word of God, by reforming Religion according to his preſcribed Will, by aſſiſting the ſpiritual Power by his temporal Sword, by Reformation of Corruption, by procuring due Obedience to the Church, by judging and cutting off all frivolous Queſtions and Schiſms, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did; and finally, by making a <hi>Decorum</hi> to be obſerved in all indifferent Things, for that purpoſe, which is the only Intent of our Oath of Supremacy.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:63430:10"/>
                  <p>My Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> out of 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>Eliz.</hi> and in the Words of the Statute gives this Interpretation: <q>There is (ſaith he) no Juriſdiction by this Act affixed to the Crown, but was of Right, or ought to be by the ancient Laws of this Realm, parcel of his Juriſdiction, and which lawfully had been, or might be exerciſed within the Realm. The End of which Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, and of all the Proceedings thereupon, is, that all Things might be in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical to the pleaſure of Almighty God, Increaſe of Vertue, and the Conſervation of the Peace and Unity of the Realm, as by divers places of the Act appears. And therefore by that Act, no pretended Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction exerciſed within this Realm, being ungodly, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the ancient Law of the Crown, was, or could be reſtored to the Crown, according to the ancient Right and Law of the ſame. <bibl>
                           <hi>Coke, de Jure Eccleſiaſtico, fol.</hi> 8.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> a great Searcher into the Doctrine of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of Kings, gives this as the Sence of the Oath. <q>The Oath (ſaith he) expreſſeth not Kings Duty to God, but ours to them: As they muſt be obeyed, when they join with Truth; ſo muſt they be endured, when they fall into Error. Which Side ſoever they take, either Obedience to their Wills, or Submiſſion to their Swords, is their due by God's Law, and that is all which our Oath exacteth.</q> And in a few Lines fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he interprets what is meant by Supremacy. <q>We do not (ſaith he) give Princes Power to do what they liſt, in the Matters appertaining to God, and his Service. Indeed we ſay, the Pope may not depoſe them, nor pull the Crown off their Heads. In this only Sence we defend them to be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, that is, not at liberty to do what they liſt, without regard of Truth or Right, but without Superior on Earth.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Morton</hi> againſt the Pope's Supremacy, out of an Epiſtle of <hi>Leo</hi> to the Emperor, ſpeaking thus: <hi>You muſt not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that your Princely Power is given unto you, not only in worldly Regiment, but alſo ſpiritual. for the Preſervation of the Church.</hi> 
                     <q>As if he had ſaid, not only in Caſes Temporal, but alſo in Spiritual, ſo far as it belongeth to the outward Preſervation, not to the perſonal Adminiſtration of them. And this is the Subſtance of our Engliſh Oath: and further, neither do our Kings of <hi>England</hi> challenge, nor Subjects condeſcend unto. <bibl>
                           <hi>pag.</hi> 26.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:63430:10"/>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Maſon</hi> in his <hi>Vindiciae Eccleſiae Angliae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> ſpeaking of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s being offended, <hi>verum ſi intellexiſſet nihil aliud ſibi voluiſſe hunc Titulum,</hi> &amp;c. <q>
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> would never have diſallowed this Oath, if he had underſtood by the Title of ſupream Governour in Eccleſiaſtical Things, that nothing elſe had been claimed, but an excluſion of Popiſh Tyranny, and a lawful Power in the King over his Subjects; which ſtands not in coyning new Articles of Faith or Forms of Religion, ſuch as were <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am's Calves;</hi> but in defending and propagating that Faith and Religion of which God in the Scripture is the undoubted Author. In this ſence and <hi>no other</hi> that ever we have heard of, is the Title of Supream Governour given to, and accepted by the King.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 5. This Oath hath matters contained in it, (as you may perceive) that are not of one nature and kind; the Aſſent and Stipulation required of us, in reſpect to the ſeveral parts of it, is likewiſe various and different: As our Creed according to the different nature of the Articles, is believed by the different Acts of Faith. To what is contained in the former part of the Oath in theſe Words; <hi>I do utterly teſtify and declare in my Conſcience, that the</hi> King's <hi>Highneſs is the only Supream Governour of this Realm,</hi> &amp;c. Herein is required a true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and cordial Aſſent to, and Profeſſion of what is mentioned; as alſo to give this Teſtimony with ſuch Sincerity of Heart as in the Preſence of God. To ſwear poſitively to any dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Aſſertion, is not required; it would be taking the Name of God in vain: for if it be a certain and undoubted Truth in it ſelf and to others; as are Principles in Reaſon and Articles of Faith; an Oath is vain, for it <hi>ends no Strife.</hi> 2. If doubtful,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> and a queſtion whether true or not, though ſuch an Oath puts it out of queſtion that I believe ſo; yet not that it is a Truth. My Belief though ever ſo much evidenced and confirmed, doth not make a doubtful matter it ſelf more credible; nor is one Man's believing an Aſſertion any juſt ground for another Man to believe the ſame; ſuch an Oath is therefore in vain, it's not a fit <hi>medium</hi> to end ſuch a Controverſy. 2. It is further ſaid, <hi>I do utterly renounce and forſake all Forreign Iurisdictions,</hi> &amp;c. This requires not only the Sincerity of my Perſwaſion and Profeſſion againſt the Title and Claim of all foraign Powers;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63430:11"/>but upon Oath to forſake, that is to abjure (we abjure when we ſwear to quit and forſake.) To forſake a Power or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, is to refuſe, and not to receive, ſubmit, or yield Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to any Commands given by it, or make any Appeals or Complaints to it. 3. That which followeth, and wherein the main of this Engagement lieth, is in theſe Words, <hi>I do promiſe that from henceforth I ſhall hear Faith,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and to my Power ſhall aſſiſt all Iuriſdictions,</hi> &amp;c. Herein is required a <hi>Promiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> Oath, ſwearing Allegiance to the King, (as a Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) to ſubmit to his Laws, as alſo if there be occaſion; to my Power to aſſiſt and defend him, and all Juriſdictions and Priviledges belonging to him. Though my Perſwaſion be ever ſo right, my Reſolution ever ſo ſincere, at the taking of this Oath; that's not all is required. In an <hi>Aſſertory</hi> Oath, if there be Truth and a right Frame of Heart in time I ſwear, and give my Teſtimony, it ſufficeth: But a <hi>Promiſſory</hi> Oath is not diſcharged by this, that I ſincerely intend what I ſay and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for I engage to Action, and for the time to come; I muſt not only promiſe, but (if it be lawful and poſſible) I muſt act and do accordingly, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. <hi>If a Man ſwear an Oath to bind his Soul with a Bond, he ſhall do according to all that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of his Mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What is meant by Perſons and things Spiritual or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical; in the proper, as alſo in the vulgar uſe of theſe Terms.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF this Expreſſion <hi>Spiritual,</hi> be interpreted by the Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Member, <hi>Temporal,</hi> it ſeems to direct us, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſuch matters as concern <hi>Eternity,</hi> for that is the true Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to what is <hi>temporal:</hi> 2 Cor. 4.18. <hi>The things that are ſeen are temporal, and the things that are not ſeen, are eternal:</hi> now in ſtrictneſs of Speech <hi>carnal,</hi> not <hi>temporal,</hi> is the oppoſite Member <hi>to ſpiritual; I could not ſpeak unto you as</hi> ſpiritual <hi>Men, but as to</hi> carnal; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>If we have ſown unto you</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63430:11"/>
                  <hi>things, is it a great matter if we reap your</hi> carnal <hi>things?</hi> But this is too narrow and ſtrict a Senſe. There are matters <hi>vulgarly</hi> termed Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical, being ſuch in Name and Title only, having nothing of a ſpiritual Nature in them-Such a Diſtinction of ſpiritual things you have in a Letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th</hi> to his Clergy, of the Province of <hi>York,</hi> in the Year 1533, who were offended at his Title of being <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Head of the Church:</hi> 
                  <q>Men (ſaith he) being here them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves earthly and temporal, cannot be Head and Governour to things eternal, nor yet ſpiritual; taking this word Spiritual not as in the common Speech <hi>abuſed,</hi> but as it ſignifies <hi>indeed.</hi>
                  </q> By ſpiritual things as abuſed in common Speech, he means what is given to all ſuch Perſons and Cauſes as belong to the Spiritual Court, and are termed by <hi>Civilians, cauſae vel res conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſae vel judiciales,</hi> matters of conteſt, <hi>inter partes, actorem &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and come to be determined by Sentence of the Judg in thoſe Courts. By thoſe things that are <hi>indeed</hi> ſpiritual, is meant <hi>res extra judiciales,</hi> or <hi>non contentioſae;</hi> that is, ſuch things as are determined not in a Judicial, or <hi>Court</hi>-way of Tryal, by Witneſſes, Oaths, Interpleadings, Sentences, and the like; but in a more deliberate and ſynodical way, having the Word of God for Witneſs and Judg; both in reſpect of what we do, and what we may do in things of this Nature. <hi>Cauſes Eazle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Field</hi>) <hi>are of two ſorts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Field</hi> of the Church <hi>p. 680.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for ſome are originally and naturally ſuch, and ſome only in that they are referred to the Cognizance of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, as the probat of the Teſtaments, Matrimony,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe Spiritual Courts being continued; and the ſame <hi>Cauſes</hi> tried in them as before, when this Juriſdiction was uſurped; the matters that were then, are ſtill vulgarly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Spiritual.</p>
               <p>Emperors receiving the Chriſtian Faith, honoured the learned and godly Biſhops antiently with ſome Juriſdiction, in the caſes of Tythes, Matrimony, Wills and the like; which are termed Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual; not from their own Nature, but from the <hi>Quality</hi> of the Perſons who were made Judges of them. They being <hi>ſpiritual Men;</hi> the Cauſes come to be called <hi>ſpiritual Cauſes</hi> (after their Names and Quality) that were ſet over them. Theſe Cauſes growing and increaſing in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, according as ſpiritual Perſons were able by the Popes aſſiſtance, to rifle from Princes; the managing of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63430:12"/>more hands, than thoſe to whom firſt committed, namely the Biſhops, and ſuch as were in holy Orders, they therefore took in for Aſſiſtants, a great number of others, as <hi>Archdeacons, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, Commſſiaries, Officials, &amp;c.</hi> and theſe are denominated Spiritual from thoſe <hi>Cauſes,</hi> and their <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of Biſhops in the managing of them: and their Courts, Spiritual Courts.</p>
               <p>There are <hi>Perſons</hi> that are truly ſpiritual, <hi>The ſpiritual Man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) judgeth all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Ye that are ſpiritual,</hi> &amp;c. That is, ſuch as have Grace and Holineſs. He alſo that hath ſpiritual Gifts, and in a Goſpel-Office or Calling, is a ſpiritual Perſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.37. <hi>a Man of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.17.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5.</note> And there are <hi>Matters</hi> or <hi>Cauſes</hi> that are truly ſpiritual; as <hi>the Law is ſpiritual,</hi> Rom. 7. The Goſpel and preaching of it, is <hi>a ſowing of ſpiritual things;</hi> 1 Cor. 9. the Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. <hi>and</hi> 14.12.</note> and all Gifts and Ordinances of Chriſt, are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual. Yea whatſoever things natural, or moral, that are helps to the Perſons worſhipping; and by which the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it ſelf becomes more orderly and to Edification, and in the defect whereof <hi>the Name of God is taken in vain,</hi> and Ordinances of Chriſt become leſs acceptable and effectual: theſe Things and Circumſtances, in ſome ſence may be termed Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical. Perſons and Cauſes of each ſort, whether <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly</hi> or <hi>properly,</hi> termed Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical, are ſome way or other under the Magiſtrates Government.</p>
               <p>The former of theſe, thoſe ſpiritual Perſons and Courts, and Cauſes appertaining to them in the firſt framing of this Oath, were principally (if not only) intended and aimed at, as appeareth in the Statutes before mentioned. And indeed the greateſt Contention between the Pope and our Princes in all time hath been about Eccleſiaſtical Matters of that nature; being then judged of greateſt prejudice in reſpect both to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Wealth</hi> of this Nation. For, thoſe matters more truly ſpiritual, and nearly relating to God and his Service (the Ignorance of the times was ſuch) his Impoſitions, both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worſhip (though very ſinful, unſound, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious) were generally recelved by Prince and People in this Nation, without reſiſting or complaining.</p>
               <p>There can be no queſtion but theſe matters being indeed temporal, properly belong to the Secular Powers. For, for the ſpace of three hundred Years, this Diſtinction was not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63430:12"/>known (ſaith Sir <hi>John Davis</hi>) or heard of in the Chriſtian World; the Cauſes of <hi>Teſtaments, Matrimony,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir <hi>J. D.</hi> in his Reports, the Caſe of <hi>Premunire.</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. termed Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical or Spiritual were meerly Civil, and determined by the Civil Laws of the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>And for Perſons and Cauſes Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical, that are properly and <hi>indeed</hi> ſuch, as firſt-Table-Duties, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain matters of Faith and Holineſs, and what conduceth to the eternal Wellfare of Mens Souls; an Intereſt and Duty there is in the Civil Magiſtrate <hi>more ſuo,</hi> to give Commands, and exerciſe lawful Juriſdiction about things of that nature. And for Perſons, there is no Man for his Graces ſo ſpiritual, or in reſpect of his Gifts and Office ſo eminent; but he is under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Civil Powers in the Place where he lives, as much in all reſpects as any other Subject.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Of Power, its riſe and original. <hi>2.</hi> Two ſorts of Power in Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual Things. <hi>3.</hi> Their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and, <hi>4.</hi> Difference of the one from the other.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 1. THere is a difference between <hi>Potentia</hi> and <hi>Poteſtas Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Strength, Force, Robuſtneſs.</hi> Such a Power is found not only in Men, particular Perſons, as <hi>Sampſon, Goliah,</hi> &amp;c. but in other inferior Creatures. <hi>Poteſtas</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Juriſdiction, Authority,</hi> this is peculiar to rational Creatures,<note place="margin">Job 40.18.</note> and as they are a Commonalty and in Society one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Though Force and Strength as in ſingular Perſons be ſufficient for publick Actions, yet without Authority, we act not lawfully; and having Authority, if we have not Power and Strength ſufficient, we cannot act effectually, therefore joyned together in a King. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.37.</p>
                  <p>All Men by Nature are equal; yet, in the firſt forming of Man, a Capacity is found in him, with ſome remote Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to rule and obey; as, 1. A Sociableneſs, <hi>let us make Man in our Image; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> and <hi>Our,</hi> a Trinity in One his Creator: Hence in each Man's Conſtitution, a Propenſion and natural bent to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63430:13"/>Union. This God himſelf obſerves, <hi>It is not good for Man. to be alone:</hi> the Woman is created, not only for a Companion, but that Men and Women might increaſe and be multiplied. 2. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Men if not reduced into Subordination and Order, having loſt their original Righteouſneſs, will be a greater Evil than if each were alone by himſelf. One Man will exalt himſelf ever others, and according to that <hi>brutiſh Force</hi> and Strength wherein he excelleth, rob, oppreſs, murther and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage others. 3. Hence a neceſſity of <hi>Republicks</hi> and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals, that ſome Rules and Laws may be provided not only for Direction, but for Correction if need be. 4. Such Laws im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Authority, and a <hi>Supremacy</hi> alſo in it; for ſuch Authority or Juriſdiction only is Legiſlative.</p>
                  <p>Man conſiſts of Soul and Body. This Principle of Civility or Sociableneſs (whence Authority hath its Original and Riſe) is placed primarily in the Soul. Society and Republicks are for the <hi>moral</hi> Good of Mens Souls therefore, and not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the Body only. The Powers alſo that are, being <hi>ordained of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> who is <hi>the Father of Spirits,</hi> ought to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and directed to Matters wherein our Souls and Spirits are concerned. The Good and Evil for which theſe <hi>Powers</hi> are <hi>ordained</hi> is not limited to the Body or outward Man.</p>
                  <p>The Power of Parents and Maſters in the Family, it is civil, not ſacred, yet ordained for the bringing up Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants <hi>in the Nurture of the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.4.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>There being a new Creation in and through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Theſe Perſons created of God, <hi>partake of a Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and thence the like Propenſion to Union and a holy Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with thoſe whom Chriſt hath redeemed out of the World. Therefore a ſpecial Proviſion is made by the Lord Jeſus for ſuch, to joyn together in particular Societies or Churches, Himſelf being appointed by his Father to be their King and Law-giver, who hath left them Rules and Laws for managing the Affairs of theſe ſpiritual Corporations or <hi>Brotherhoods</hi> (as the Scripture terms them); Power alſo and Authority for putting theſe Laws in execution is given unto Churches. So that there is a twofold Power or Authority, to be exerciſed in Cauſes, and over Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, the one placed in the Princes, the other in the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:63430:13"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The difference betwixt theſe two Powers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Neceſſity if the Civil Power in Eccleſiaſtial Matters, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Church-Power.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p n="2">§. 2. What is common to both, and wherein each of theſe Powers differ from the other, ſhall briefly be ſhewed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They are <hi>Powers,</hi> both a Subordination or Policy in the Church as well as in the Common-weal, and an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or Juriſdiction exerciſed in each. You read of Authority or Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction not only in Civil Aſſemblies, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>John</hi> 19.11. but alſo in Churches, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. and 13.10. the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in both places.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They are both from God, and the Ordinance of God, and ought to be ſubmitted to <hi>for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and are for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to thoſe that are Good, and for Wrath upon him that doth Evil; and he that reſiſteth this Power in either, <hi>reſiſts the Ordinance of God,</hi> and they that reſiſt receive to themſelves Damnation (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) as well in reſpect to the one as the other. And both being from God, they are alſo both Powers <hi>under God,</hi> that is, under his Deſignment and Limits, as alſo his Direction and Guidance; for his Glory, as the ultimate; and the good of Mankind, as the penultimate end of both.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This Power of Princes is termed ſpiritual, <hi>Ratione objecti,</hi> becauſe it hath to do with Spiritual Perſons and Cauſes. In ſuch like a ſenſe and manner of Speech (if it had the ſtamp of vulgar Uſe) the Church-Power, may be termed Civil or Temporal; becauſe all ſorts of Perſons and Cauſes without Difference are under the Power of it. That as the ſecular Power is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Tabulae,</hi> matters of Holineſs (and what's oppoſite to it, Blaſphemy, Hereſy, Perjury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as well as Righteouſneſs; ſo Church-Power is <hi>Cuſtos utriusque Tabulae,</hi> Righteouſneſs and ſecond-Table-Duties, and what is oppoſite, as Rebellion, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Lying, Stealing; if any Man that is <hi>called a Brother, be a Fornicator, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner,</hi> &amp;c. In all theſe and ſuch Caſes the Church-Power is applied in an Eccleſiaſtical, or Spiritual way; as in a Civil and Secular way the Magiſtrate deals with what are Duties of the firſt Table.</p>
                  <p>The Powers do mutually further each other, and ſo ordained by God, (from whom they are both originally) as they ſweetly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63430:14"/>comply and agree (being kept in their juſt Bounds) each with other; as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, David</hi> and <hi>Nathan, Zerubbabel</hi> the Son <hi>Shealtiel,</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Joſedech. Jungamus Gladios,</hi> ſaid the Emperor to his Biſhop, let us joyn our Forces and purge the Land of Wickedneſs. And our Senators in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſpeak thus of theſe;<note place="margin">Stat. 20. <hi>Hen</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Both Authorities and Juriſdictions joyn together, and the one helps the other.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <p n="3">§. 3. Their Differences are in theſe Particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Though both have (in their reſpective way) to do with both Tables, yet the Civil Magiſtrates Work lyeth moſt over Perſons with reſpect to the Duties of the ſecond Table; as in matters of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and Righteouſneſs; in the managing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the very being of a Common-wealth principally conſiſts; its wel-being, only as he hath to do in Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes. So the Church-Power is chiefly and principally exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the ordering of Perſons, with reſpect to the firſt-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Duties, and which appertains to <hi>Piety:</hi> Wherein is the Being and conſtant Employment of Churches. The other, that is, matters of Righteouſneſs, Juſtice, Sobriety, and the like, are occaſionally only and <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> under Church-Power and Cenſures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Power of Churches is not only ſpiritual <hi>Ratione objecti,</hi> becauſe its over ſpiritual Perſons and Cauſes; but <hi>ex natura rei,</hi> a ſpiritual Power having Spirituality, and its Denomination from more intrinſick Conſiderations, as the Matter, Form, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Rule, End, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not from the Object only, as that other Power; which though it be in ſpiritual things, yet it is not properly ſpiritual Power, the Sword which it bears is not <hi>the Sword of the Spirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 1.16.</note> Epheſ. 6. <hi>which is the Word of God,</hi> and this Word is eternal, not temporal, <hi>it endureth for ever,</hi> the Power and Soveraignty of it is from Chriſt; <hi>out of his Mouth went a ſharp two-edged Sword:</hi> his Sword and Power being ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, it <hi>pierceth,</hi> runs deep, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. even <hi>betwixt the Soul and the Spirit;</hi> there comes no ſuch Sword or Law from Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: that Power in its greateſt Efficacy, reacheth not the Inner-Man, though to be ſubmitted unto for Conſcience ſake. Indeed this Power is over ſpiritual Perſons, but not immediately and directly over their ſpiritual part: By theſe Powers we are given up to a Priſon, to Baniſhment, to Death,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63430:14"/>but not to Satan. It is not for cruciating the Souls, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing the Conſciences of Men, as is Church-Power, where there is Cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That of Secular Magiſtrates, even in Spiritual Affairs, and having to do primarily with the outward Man, is more Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative; it is <hi>Juriſdictio propriè dicta, Legiſlative, Coercive,</hi> and in all reſpects the ſame as in Civil Matters, what he doth in his own Name. And truly <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Church-Power, is not properly Juriſdiction or Authority, as in the Church, but as in Chriſt; the Head of the Church; as ſeated in the Church, or <hi>Caetus fidelium,</hi> it is only <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Miniſterium,</hi> not <hi>Demini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and acts all in the Name or Authority of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They differ in Extenſion, in reſpect to both Perſons and Cauſes. 1. Church-Power is limited to a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, as Family-Power to thoſe of our own Houſhold: But this other Eccleſiaſtical Power, ſeated in the ſame Perſon or Perſons, extends it ſelf throughout a whole Kingdom, yea, ſometimes to more than one. But in ſome one Province or Kingdom, you read in Scripture of many Churches. This co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſs from another Difference between theſe Powers: The Manage of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as in Civil Magiſtrates, may be delegated to other hands, by way of Commiſſion or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; they may ordain under them ſubordinate Thrones, and inferior Powers, acting in their Names, which is Lordly, and full of Honour and State: But Churches may not do ſo, by delegation of Power, Repreſentatives, or any other Method or Way, to ſtretch forth the Wing of their Authority (like that of the Civil) over all the Churches of a Nation, or over more Congregations than one, or a greater than ordinarily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of all other Ordinances together, is not at all ſuitable to a Church-Condition, which is Miniſterial, not Lordly. So Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> as the Opinion of the Nonconformiſts: <q>We confine and bound all Eccleſiaſtical Power within the Limits only of one particular Congregation, holding, that the greateſt Eccleſiaſtical Power ought not to ſtretch beyond the ſame: And that it is an arrogating of Princely Supremacy, for any Eccleſiaſtical Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, to take upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction over many Churches, much more over whole Kingdoms, and Provinces of Churches.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:63430:15"/>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſpeaks much to this purpoſe:<note place="margin">Of Supremacy, <hi>pag.</hi> 238.</note> 
                     <q>Tho (ſaith he) Biſhops may be called Governors in reſpect of the Soul, yet only Princes be Governors of Realms. Paſtors have Flocks, and Biſhops have Dioceſſes; Realms, Dominions, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries none have, but Princes and Magiſtrates. And ſo the Stile, <hi>Governor of this Realm,</hi> belongeth only to the Prince, and not to the Prieſt, and importeth a Publick and Princely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment. The Common-Wealth (ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the People in a whole Nation,<note place="margin">Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, <hi>pag.</hi> 220.</note> or more, as united in one Sovereign: But particular Churches have no general Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Officers, in whom a Nation muſt unite as one Church, but are as ſeveral Corporations in one Kingdom,</q> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. We ſee</hi> (ſaith Sir <hi>Fr. Bacon</hi>) <hi>in all Laws in the World,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about Church-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</note> 
                     <hi>Offices of Confidence and Skill cannot be exerciſed by Delegation, all ſuch Truſt is</hi> perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>and inherent, and may not be tranſported and delegated, as that of Kings, which for the moſt part is hereditary, and rather an Office of Intereſt than Confidence.</hi> 2. In reſpect to Cauſes, the Church-Power extends its Cenſures to no Cauſes, but ſuch as the other may, as to Popery, Hereſy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But in many Caſes the Civil Magiſtrate extends his Care and Authority, where Church-Power moddles not: As to Jews and Pagans, and ſuch as are not Members of the Church; ſome things may be done by the Magiſtrate even for theſe, being Members of his Common-Wealth, that may conduce to their ſpiritual Good. The Church-Power is limited, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. So likewiſe whether the Crime committed be private or publick, Matter of Scandal, or not, or the Perſon penitent, or otherwiſe, theſe Powers are at liberty to puniſh or pardon alike, and as they ſhall judg it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, to be ſevere or merciful accordingly. They may form or reform the Laws and Statutes by which they govern;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz. cap</hi> 1. with 35 <hi>Hen</hi> 8.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſame Fault Treaſon in one Age, that in the next not ſo much as Impriſonment. But Church-Power is limited, the ſame Crime, the ſame Puniſhment ever, not being in the Power of this Republick to vary in their Proceſs, in reſpect of leſſer or greater Cenſures, if the Crime be ſhe ſame.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In their Conſtitution or Tenure: <hi>Licet omnis Poteſtas</hi> (ſaith <hi>Carbo</hi>) <hi>tum Eccleſiaſtica tum Civilis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Carbo</hi> de Leg. iib. 2. cap. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>ſit à Deo, tamen non eodem modo; nam politica licet univerſe ſit jure Divino, in particulari eſt jure Gentium, Eccleſiaſtica omni modo eſt jure divino, &amp; à Deo.</hi> Government in general is of Divine Right, but whether in this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63430:15"/>or that particular Form, as in one, or a few repreſenting the reſt, this is humane, and hath its Original from Man. That Power which is termed an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. is called an <hi>Ordinance of Man,</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. Church-Power and Government being ſpiritual, hath all particulars for ſubſtance, both in reſpect of Perſons and Adminiſtrations, for matter and manner appointed by Jeſus Chriſt, and in all Nations to be the ſame. Civil Power, even in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, in many things for ſubſtance, is left to the Prudence of the State in which it is exerciſed; and in the Forms of it various, according to the manner of the Nation. As for Inſtance; Inſpection into Religious Aſſemblies, viſiting and obſerving their Demeanour, receiving Complaints, by reaſon of Wrongs, Diſorders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe things may be done by the Civil Magiſtrate, in his own Perſon, or by Perſons authorized from him; theſe Perſons may be many, or but one in a Diviſion, theſe Diviſions of larger or leſs Compaſs. And for the manner of Procedure, it's various, as Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Courts differ in their manner of Proceſs from Civil, or of a Method or Way of handling Cauſes different from each, be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law, it is equally warrantable. There are particular Directions left by Chriſt, according to which the Officers (and Perſons more eſpecially entruſted with this Power) are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to, and inveſted in their Places and Charge, as <hi>Election, Ordination,</hi> &amp;c. with Faſting and Prayer. The other Powers are ſetled upon, and claimed in ſuch ways, as the reſpective Law of Nations deſign, as by Birth, Lot, Victory, Donation, or the like, as well as Election; inſomuch as a Woman or Child may have a rightful Claim to this Supreme Truſt, and the Management of it, by themſelves or others, as ſhall be appointed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63430:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>§. 1.</hi> Of the Neceſſity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of a Juriſdiction over Perſons, and in Cauſes Eccleſiastical, beſides what is in Churches. <hi>§. 2.</hi> This Power is placed in Kings, and ſuch as are the Supreme Governors in a Common-Wealth.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>§.</hi> 1. FOr the <hi>ſecond,</hi> we ſhall ſhew how neceſſary and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Civil Power</hi> is, even in Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual Matters, notwithſtanding the other. It is not to be denied, that Souls were converted, and Churches eſtabliſhed, and kept up, when there was no Aſſiſtance, but rather Oppoſition, from the Princes of the Earth, as in the Apoſtolick and Primitive Times. The Benefit we have now by Chriſtian Mgiſtrates, was then more abundantly ſupplied, (the Infancy of Chriſtianity requiring more) by the Miracles wrought, and the conſtant Direction and Care of Apoſtolick and extraordinary Perſons, who were gifted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> for that purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>All the ordinary Helps that now we have, by external and more ſenſual or carnal Means, contributing any thing to theſe great Works, is only a pious and <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtracy,</hi> where a Nation is bleſſed with it. The Benefit hereof is much in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual reſpect, both to the <hi>World,</hi> as likewiſe to the <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is (tho remote) a great Help to bring Men out of their natural Condition, unto Life and Salvation. We are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>pray for Kings, and ſuch as are in Authority,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. The reaſon, v. 4. <hi>For God will have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledg of the Truth.</hi> As the Knowledg of the Truth is a means to bring a Soul into a ſaving State; ſo is the Magiſtrate (being enlightned himſelf) a great Means to bring us to the knowledg of the Truth. Thoſe Men were in a great Diſtance from God, in a Rage againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and Religion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1. they did combine againſt the ſtrict Ways of the Goſpel; theſe poor Heathens being, notwithſtanding, given to <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Election, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>David</hi> uſeth a twofold Method for reducing them: The firſt is,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63430:16"/>a repreſenting their wretched and miſcrable Condition, while in this State of Enmity, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. Then, 2. deals with their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Rulers, to be forthwith inſtructed, and ſerve the Lord, <hi>i.e.</hi> as Kings and Magiſtrates, in their publick Capacity. But muſt not the People be inſtructed alſo? Such Magiſtrates will ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provide and take care for their People, that they may be brought to the knowledg of the Truth; and therefore it needs not to be mentioned.</p>
                  <p>The Magiſtratical Power conduceth to this Work divers ways, 1. By ſetting up and protecting a Goſpel-Miniſtry. He only can ſubſerve Providence, by ſending, or giving way to others to ſend forth fit Perſons, and enforce a Maintenance for their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in this Work. By ſuch a Word of Providence (it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) we come to <hi>hear,</hi> and by hearing we believe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. He can urge his People to come to the Means, and outwardly conform to the ſame, and ſo bring them to the Knowledg of the Truth, the very Knowledg whereof, tho not ſaving, is a means at leaſt to reſtrain our inbred Corruption, and to work preparatively to Converſion, bringing Men into a Condition <hi>not far from the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> as Chriſt ſpeaks.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.20.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Civil Magiſtrate hath Power to puniſh and reward, and ſo to work upon the Paſſions of <hi>Fear, Deſire, Hope,</hi> &amp;c. Man, even in his Natural Eſtate, hath free Will in Moral Actions, if it be excited and drawn forth. The Paſſions are ſo ſeated betwixt the Will and Senſes, that outward and ſenſual Objects work ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually upon it: the Motions of the Will, in this our State of Corruption, depending more upon the viſions of what is ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,<note place="margin">Hominem etſi timore poenae fugiat pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, paulatian affectum &amp; animum ad illud amittere, &amp; è contrario concipere odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um illius, idec<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> etiam vitare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Ariag.</hi> de Leg. <hi>Diſp. 13. § 9. Hoſ. 2.6.</hi>
                     </note> than what is a rational Good or Evil. The moſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſtirring Paſſion, and with moſt life and vigour, in a natural Man, is Self, or Self-Love; it is the firſt Principle uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that God excites in us towards Converſion, as in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Prodigal, and divers other Scriptures. Sickneſs, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and the like Occurrence of Providences, (Puniſhments for Sin) being ſanctified by the Lord, work much upon us; ſo Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries inflicted upon the more obſtinate, from Magiſtrates (in Juſtice for evil-doing) have the ſame Operation: and by reaſon hereof, groſs Corruptions are kept in and reſtrained, whereby the Habits of Sin decreaſe, and become leſs rank in the Soul. It is a <hi>hedging our Way with Thorns,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63430:17"/>
                  <p>A great part of the World lies without the Pale of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the ſeverity of its Judicature reacheth them not. This Power is exerciſed only on Church-Members; we have nothing to do to <hi>judg them that are without,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.12, 13.</note> tho they be <hi>Fornicators, or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, or Idolaters, or Drunkards, or Extortioners;</hi> Churches, in reſpect of Cenſures and Puniſhment, leave them to God by the Magiſtrate, or the like Providential way to judg them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Impedimenta removendo;</hi> he removes corrupt Teachers, that ſlay Mens Souls,<note place="margin">Mich. 2.11.</note> by crying Peace, propheſying of Wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> indulging Sinners in their Security; and ſuch as by Errors and falſe Doctrine poyſon Mens Souls, to their eternal perdition; by reſtaining Stage-Plays, not permitting Brothel-Houſes, and the like Fomenters of Sin.</p>
                  <p>Now there is no means or proviſion ſo certain, and generally effectual to ſend out Preachers, to urge and conſtrain Men to hear, and for all theſe purpoſes, as this, when the Magiſtrate, according to his Truſt and Duty, puts forth his Authority in theſe Matters; or that will ſo univerſally, as an external means, ſtir that Principle of Self-love in all Men, to the ſeeking after what is good, and the ſhunning of what is evil. A <hi>Coercive</hi> Power of this Nature is placed in no other hand but his. Miniſters may preach and perſuade,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.3. Mat. 20.</note> but muſt be <hi>no Strikers,</hi> may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally afflict and conſtrain; <hi>Peter</hi> may not uſe his Sword in Chriſt's Quarrel. God only, and the Civil Magiſtrate, further our Happineſs, by making us miſerable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> who had as much Power as any Man of that Order, yet his Weapons were only ſpiritual; and tho an Apoſtle, yet could not do ſo much as the meaneſt Civil Magiſtrate in ſuch a Coercive way: for their Weapons will, whether Men incline or not, have an operation, and conſtant effect, leſs or more, to whomſoever applied. This Power therefore of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot well be wanted; or if it be, there is no ordinary means to be had for a ſupply in the room of it.<note place="margin">Judg. 17.6.</note> 
                     <hi>When there was no King in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>every Man did what was right in his own Eyes,</hi> followed the Ways his Luſts led him to. Suppoſe there be good Counſel and Inſtruction, yet to many Perſons it ſignifieth little; for ſome Men are not corrigible by Words, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.19. The <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> that is <hi>bound up in our Hearts, muſt by Correction be driven far from us.</hi> Prov. 22.15.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:63430:17"/>
                  <p n="4">4. I ſhall conclude, adding in the laſt place,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> the <hi>Praiſe of Well-doing.</hi> The Countenance and Encouragement of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to thoſe that preach, and thoſe that obey the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, renders it even to a carnal Heart deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Lord gives this honour to a poor <hi>Servant,</hi> faithful in his place, that he <hi>adorns the Goſpel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> and renders it more acceptable and effectual. So likewiſe the <hi>Converſaetion of a Wife,</hi> that thoſe <hi>who obey not the Word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1.</note> are <hi>without the Word</hi> won by ſuch a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; that is, won to the Love of the Word, and the liking of thoſe Ways that are according to the Word. Much greater is that Honour and Ornament which comes to the Goſpel, when the Magiſtrate, not only by his Converſation, and perſonal Example, but by his Laws and Authority, ſets himſelf to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all he can, the Preachers and Profeſſors thereof, bearing them up againſt Deſpiſers and Scoffers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In reſpect to the Church,<note place="margin">To the Church.</note> and ſuch as are effectually call'd out of the World; God hath promiſed, and in the Scripture much comforted his People in this, that they ſhall have great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by the Civil Magiſtrates that are over them: as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.2. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 49.23. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 60.16. Theſe Promiſes relate to Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. And thoſe Places, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.16. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. are equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to Promiſes: a <hi>Prayer</hi> is as it were a <hi>Promiſe</hi> reverſed; what is ſpoken by the Lord in a Promiſe, being returned, is the ſtrength and confidence of a Prayer. Encouragements alſo to obey Precepts, imply Promiſes; ſo that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. our Subjection is required upon this conſideration, that Kings are for <hi>the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>ordained of God to thee</hi> (to the Church, and to every Saint) <hi>for good.</hi> The Lord in this doth not only promiſe, but as it were undertake for the Magiſtrate, that he ſhall be ſuch an one, as thoſe that are pious and righteous, thoſe that do well, need not dread or fear to be under him. A good Magiſtrate is a Bleſſing, and matter of joy and rejoycing to the People of God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.2. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.17. a great Fruit and Evidence of his Love to them, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.9. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Becauſe the Lord hath loved his People, he hath made thee King over them;</hi> it is ſo ſpoken of <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Benefit and Good to the Churches and Saints from the Civil Magiſtrate, may more particularly be judged of in theſe Conſiderations.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:63430:18"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Kings and Princes are an Ordinance of God, or <hi>Medium</hi> by which, in a more ſpecial and peculiar way, he communicates his Power, Wiſdom and Juſtice for the governing of all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Men. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.28. <hi>All</hi> Iſrael <hi>feared the King, for they ſaw that the Wiſdom of God was in him, to do Judgment.</hi> So the Power and Juſtice, and the like Attributes of God, become viſible in this Ordinance of God. See <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.10. and 21.1. It is brought as an Argument to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates againſt Partiality and Bribery; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7. <hi>There is no Iniquity with the Lord our God, nor reſpects of Perſone, nor taking of Gifts.</hi> What is, or is not in God, ſhould be, or not be found in him that is a Magiſtrate. They are therefore termed <hi>Gods,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a viſible Repreſentation of God's Attributes, is, or ought to be in their Governing. And as Chriſt is ſaid to be preſent with thoſe Officers in the Church which he hath appointed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a ſpecial Virtue and Efficacy of Chriſt manifeſt in their Miniſtry: So in this great Ordinance of a Magiſtrate, there is ſaid to be a ſpecial <hi>Preſence</hi> of God with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6. From the like Manifeſtation of God, in his Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Welfare of Societies.</p>
                  <p>There is ſuch a Harmony and Neighbourhood between the outward and inward Man, that what works upon the one, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the other. When therefore the Miniſtry by Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence works upon a Man's Soul, the Man is of a better Behaviour outwardly, and to Civil Relations: So alſo being brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to outward Subjection and <hi>Conformity,</hi> (by Magiſtracy) the Mind and ſpiritual part is much the more fitted for <hi>Chriſtian Communion.</hi> Moral Vertues, yea, Civilities are much preſſed upon Church-Members every where in the Epiſtles, as to be <hi>kind, courteous,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>humble, ſubmiſs, ſelf-denying. Paul</hi> ſpends a whole Chapter in Greetings and Salutes. Men and Women that are <hi>moroſe, ſelfiſh, ſtiff, opinionative, ill-bred,</hi> ſuch for the moſt part are burthenſom in all, and as much in theſe ſpiritual Societies as in any other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For Protection, Church-Power neither judgeth or reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>them that are without;</hi> it is no Fence nor Security againſt the World. The only Hedg about this Vineyard, under God, is the Sword of the Civil Magiſtrate. Saints and Churches, being called and ſeparated out of the World, are hated by the World, and ſuch a Seed of Enmity in them againſt the Members of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63430:18"/>Chriſt; as if there were no higher Power to reſtrain, being the far greater number, they would utterly root us out.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Church</hi> for Weakneſs and Helpleſneſs is reſembled by a <hi>Nurſe-Child,</hi> or Infant, which needs the Care of thoſe who have more Strength. This religious Care and Tenderneſs, is,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.16.</note> or ought to be in the Magiſtrate, who is termed a <hi>Nurſe.</hi> The Prophet in this Promiſe hath an Eye to Goſpel-Times, and Churches, called together amongſt the Gentiles. In an Age when there would be no Prophets or Apoſtles, or <hi>Signs, or Wonders, or mighty Deeds</hi> wrought in the behalf of the Church,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.12.</note> as was in the Jewiſh Oeconomy, and firſt Age of Chriſtians. It's promiſed that Kings and Princes (either by a common or ſaving Change) ſhall become nurſing Fathers,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.6, 9. 1 Kings 4.29.</note> nouriſhing and protecting Chriſt's feeble Orphant the Church. And where the Magiſtrate is ſuch, we ought to pray that all may be ſuch; we have the Liberty under them (notwithſtanding the World's Enmity) to lead a <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> Life,<note place="margin">1 Kings 4.29.</note> and this not only in <hi>Honeſty,</hi> but in all <hi>Godlineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Judgments of God, Sword of the Magiſtrate, and the like external Adminiſtrations are helpful to the beſt of Men, who are liable, while a Body of Sin, to as foul external Acts of Sin, as the worſt of Men. The ſpiritual part in us by theſe means, helps it ſelf much (in an hour of Temptation eſpecially) againſt the Fleſh, over-ballancing the Pleaſures of Sin, from that Shame and Grief Sin brings with it; ſo that <hi>Self-love,</hi> or a higher Principle is hereby ſtrengthened to avert us. Servile Fear (evil only in defect) is good and uſeful to the beſt of us, while in a mixed Condition, and not perfect in our Love to God. <hi>Joh</hi> was eminently <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> yet in both much furthered from the Conſideration of Wrath and Judgment.<note place="margin">Job 31.19, 21, <hi>with</hi> 23.</note> 
                     <hi>If I have ſeen</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>any periſh for want of Cloathing; If I have lift up my Hand againſt the Fatherleſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>For</hi> Deſtruction <hi>from God was a Terror to me.</hi> The Magiſtrates Eccleſiaſtical Power had the like effect to reſtrain <hi>Impiety</hi> in him, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 26, 27, 28. <hi>If I beheld the Sun, and my Heart hath been ſecretly enticed, or my Mouth hath kiſſed my Hand: this were an Iniquity to be puniſhed by the Judg.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> though <hi>conſtrained by Love,</hi> verſ. 14. Such was his Affection to Chriſt, yet moved alſo to Duty from the Conſideration of <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Terror,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.11.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63430:19"/>
                  <p>If it be thus with the beſt of the Saints, much more will Churches ſtand in need of ſuch an external Help againſt Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: There being not only a mixture of Fleſh and Spirit, in thoſe that are Members <hi>indeed;</hi> but a mixture with them of Hypocrites, and ſuch as are Members only <hi>in ſhew.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We find in the Churches planted by the Apoſtles, a uſe not only of Spiritual Cenſures,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> but alſo outward and bodily Afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Sickneſs, Weakneſs,</hi> &amp;c. for Church-Miſcarriages; and it's ſaid to be <hi>for the Salvation of their Souls,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> Chap. 5. ver. 5. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 32. So that Severity of the Lord on <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> was for a Church-Fault, and it's ſaid <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Great Fear came upon all the Church.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> It was an eminent Church, before whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſhakes the Magiſtrate's Sword, and tells them, if they do that which is evil, they have cauſe to be afraid, <hi>for he beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Afflictions</hi> that are from a more immediate Hand of God, either in an ordinary or an extraordinary way, thoſe alſo that the Lord chaſtiſeth us with by the Hand of the Magiſtrate, I difference not, each being to the ſame purpoſe, and as an external Diſcipline. For where there are no Magiſtrates, or negligent ones, God in a providential way, and more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately judgeth and afflicts Evil-doers; even as where Church-Diſcipline is wanting or neglected, God himſelf <hi>excommunicates</hi> as it were, and gives Men up to Terror and Anguiſh of Soul, for their evil Deeds.</p>
                  <p>If we ſhould draw in here Inſtances from the Jewiſh Church, and how the Lord diſciplined them by the Civil Magiſtrate, and afflicting the outward Man, there can be nothing more evident than this, an undoubted Uſefulneſs of ſuch Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, even to the Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And although it ſhould not be a good reaſoning, to argue from what Power the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> exerciſed in reſpect of its <hi>Extent</hi> in Particulars;<note place="margin">a Chron. 8 14.</note> many of them being <hi>Prophets</hi> as well as Princes; yet the Benefit and Uſefulneſs of ſuch Power may be the ſame unto <hi>us</hi> as unto <hi>them,</hi> both in reſpect of Terror to <hi>Evil-Doers,</hi> and Praiſe to them that <hi>do well.</hi> Though an Argument from <hi>Circumciſion</hi> applied to Infants, will not weigh with ſome, becauſe they deny <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to be a Sacrament of that Nature: Yet this cannot be denied by them, that if an <hi>Infant</hi> be capable of Benefit by an Ordinance it underſtands not;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63430:19"/>Infants may as lawfully in that reſpect be <hi>baptiſed</hi> whille In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, as they were then <hi>circumciſed.</hi> The Arguments brought from Eccleſiaſtical Power exerciſed by Magiſtrates in the Jewiſh Government, will argue at leaſt that there is a <hi>Capacity</hi> in Men <hi>now</hi> to receive Benent and Good thereby (even in ſpiritual Matters) as they did then; which is all that is aimed at.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As it is the Duty of each Perſon,<note place="margin">Col 2.</note> ſo of Churches <hi>to walk wiſely towards them that are without,</hi> that their <hi>Order</hi> may be looked upon, not only with <hi>Rejoycing</hi> by Neighbour-Churches, but ſuch as may appear <hi>amiable</hi> and <hi>comely</hi> in the Eyes of all Men. There are many things common to all Societies, which Nature and civil Cuſtoms inſtruct us in, and are eſpecially to be heeded by Churches. For as the things <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Lovely</hi> in the Eyes of Men, being neglected by <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> will ſuffer, ſo much more if by <hi>Churches.</hi> The outward <hi>Beauty</hi> of theſe Chriſtian Aſſemblies, conſiſts very much in what is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and comely in all human Societies; as Unity, Love, Peace, brotherly Forbearance, <hi>&amp;c. Let all things,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>be done without murmuring or diſputing. Paul</hi> charged the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> with this, that there were <hi>Debates, Envyings, Wrath, Strifes, Back-bitings, Whiſperings, Swellings, Tumults,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.20.</note> and the like amongſt them. There may be Wrongs and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Churches, as in other Aſſemblies. Innocent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons impeached and cenſured as <hi>Schiſmatiks, Seditious,</hi> and Diſturbers of the Peace; and no Remedy but from the Civil Magiſtrate. <hi>Paul</hi> appeals from the Church to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> a Secular Prince, expecting from him, though a Heathen, more <hi>Juſtice,</hi> then from his Brethren, being Parties, and in their own Cauſe. For where Parties are Judges, the Sentence is paſſed before the Cauſe is heard. As a Church may be <hi>offended;</hi> ſo they may,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10 32.</note> and oft-times do <hi>give Offence</hi> as well as ſingle Perſons. It's part of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate's Care, and as a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> to puniſh open Offenderrs, whither ſingle Perſons or Aſſemblies. And the Truth is, if ſuch Aſſemblies, that is, Churches, be not under the Magiſtrates Juriſdiction, they are under none, and will be at a loſs in reſpect of all thoſe Advantages before mentioned.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> of this Power being declared ſo fully, it will not be difficult to evince the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> if it, that is, to the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of Churches. For whatſoever thing is uſeful in Spiritual
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63430:20"/>Affairs, is in the ſame degree neceſſary. <hi>I argue thus:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the <hi>Ruling</hi> and <hi>Coercive</hi> Power in a Church extends it ſelf no further than its own Members; if one particular Church cannot <hi>ſuſpend, excommunicate,</hi> or exerciſe any the like Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over another; it will then follow, vvhatſoever benefit or advantage Churches, or their Members, are ſuppoſed to have and reap, by being under any <hi>external</hi> Ruling Power here on Earth; this may, and ought to be expected from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Eccleſiaſtical Power and no other: His being the only Power that is of ſuch an Extenſion and Compaſs, as to be over all Perſons and Societies without his Dominion,</p>
                  <p>For the further <hi>Explication</hi> and <hi>Confirming</hi> of what is aſſerted, I ſhall lay down ſome Conſiderations, and then anſwer Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Purpoſely enlarging upon this Argument, as tending much to a diſtinct underſtanding of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, both as it is in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Conſiderations are theſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>1</label> There is no Power or Authority either in Church or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that doth <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> compel or enforce the <hi>Soul.</hi> Pains, Penalties, Reſtraints, bodily Puniſhments; or what comes nearer, and is more ſpiritual, as Admonition, Suſpenſion, Excommunication, or the like. 'When Perſons in any of theſe ways are judged and cenſured, by the Church or Magiſtrate, or both; it hath its Fruit and effect in reſpect of Morals, only in a more remote and <hi>circular</hi> way, as by work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Judgment and Affections; for there is no created Power can reach the Soul, to put upon it any <hi>immediate</hi> Force or Reſtraint, further than by applying ſuch means (diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Scripture or Light of Reaſon) as are apt and ſutable to ſet the Soul and Conſcience of a Man, to work upon it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>We term it <hi>Coercive,</hi> in difference from what is only <hi>directive</hi> and <hi>perſwaſive,</hi> for according as the Lord hath appointed means to this or that end, accordingly he works, and ſo we ought to judg and ſpeak. Now beſides means appointed for <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>Perſwaſion,</hi> God alſo hath added <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> a means mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally coercive, which hath Pain and Shame, it's a Puniſhment <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and for the Deſtruction of the Fleſh,</hi> therefore a means morally <hi>Compulſive,</hi> and more than meerly perſwaſive, the <hi>Rod
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63430:20"/>and Reproof</hi> is more than a ſingle Reproof,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4 21. Prov. 29.15. Prov. 29.19.</note> it is a <hi>Correction</hi> which is <hi>compulſive; a Servant will not be corrected with Words.</hi> To make <hi>all</hi> but <hi>directive,</hi> is to confound the <hi>Keys.</hi> The Reverend Author ſhould not judg or ſpeak of an Ordinnce according to the <hi>Reception</hi> of a carnal Heart,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr. B.</hi> in his firſt Diſpute, <hi>p. 6.</hi>
                     </note> but according to what is <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned</hi> by the Lord, as his ordinary Drift and Scope in ſuch an Appointment. There is the Word <hi>read,</hi> Goſpel <hi>preached,</hi> and viſible <hi>Seals;</hi> we are to judg a greater and more effectual Exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of Chriſt in the one, than in the other, yet all alike to a carnal and unbelieving Soul.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label> 2. There are two great and Catholick <hi>Bodies,</hi> or Kingdoms, <hi>immediately</hi> and <hi>invifibly</hi> governed by the Lord and his Chriſt: The <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> made up each of leſſer Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Cities, Families,</hi> particular <hi>Churches,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, <hi>invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> and <hi>immediately:</hi> for, as God is inviſible, ſo what he acts immediately, he acts inviſibly. As the Church is diſtinguiſhed into viſible and inviſible, ſo is the Power by which it is gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Inviſible</hi> as in a ſecret and myſterious way, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from the Lord: And thus are all Kingdoms, Nations, Tongues and Languages united as in one, even the great bulk of Mankind; as alſo the Catholick Church, that great Body of Saints, they are all thus governed by the Lord, and by the Lord alone, and not by Man. <hi>Viſible,</hi> as where theſe great Bodies of Men and Chriſtians, come to be cantoned, parcelled, and formed into Political Bodies, governed by Men,<note place="margin">Whit. <hi>Tract</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. p. 181.</note> in an <hi>external</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> way.</p>
                  <p>Theſe viſible Bodies are either greater and <hi>containing,</hi> as Empires, Kingdoms, Provinces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or thoſe that are leſs, and <hi>contained,</hi> as Cities, Colledges, Pariſhes, Families, and the like, whether they be Civil or Eccleſiaſtical. Theſe leſſer, though they have the Compleatneſs of a <hi>Body</hi> or Corporation, each in its kind, and ſufficient Power to govern it <hi>ſelf;</hi> yet not to govern one <hi>another.</hi> A Church hath not Authority to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern a Church, nor a Family, or the chief in it to govern a Neighbour-Family. The Light in the leaſt <hi>Star</hi> is ſufficient for it ſelf, but not to rule the Day or the Night, as the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>leſſer</hi> Bodies are therefore ſo compoſed in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Regiments; that many of them together, may lie in the Boſom of a greater Corporation; and it will be for their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63430:21"/>and more comfortable ſubſiſting and Government.</p>
                  <p>There is no <hi>external Coercive,</hi> or ruling Power that falls in, and fills up the ſpace betwixt thoſe great and Catholick Bodies the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>the Church,</hi> and thoſe leſſer and loweſt Regiments and Societies, but what is, or ought to be expected by or from the Civil Magiſtrate, who is to be acknowledged of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil <hi>under</hi> God to be <hi>over</hi> all.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>3</label> 3. Theſe leſſer Societies therefore ordinarily are found under a twofold Regiment or Diſcipline. The one intrinſecal and <hi>peculiar,</hi> which in Families is received from the Light of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and from the Light of <hi>Inſtitution</hi> in Churches. The other more <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Common:</hi> And theſe leſſer Bodies come under it by reaſon of their <hi>Situation,</hi> being within the Confines of ſuch a Republick, they are under the Juriſdiction of the Princes thereof.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Epiſc.</hi> lib. 3. c. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Each Prince,</hi> ſaith <hi>Maſon,</hi> hath Power <hi>in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos ſuos ac proinde in Eccleſiam modo ſubditi ſunt Eccleſiae.</hi> If ſituated where there is no formed Common-wealth, King, or Supream Power over them, they are as a Free-State, each Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, City, and Church, immediately under God and Chriſt, and no other Power but what it hath in it ſelf; which being a Power not derived from the Magiſtrate, but peculiar to a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or Church, remains in them, though no Magiſtrate. Such was the Family and Church-ſtate in the time of the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> for two thouſand Years.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>4</label> As it is a Happineſs to a People that live in Empires and Kingdoms, that theſe are parcels of that World which hath the righteous God to govern it, who is <hi>the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 19.15.</note> So is it likewiſe to theſe leſſer Bodies, a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or a Church, that they are ſituated under the Wing of a Chriſtian, and well-governed Common-wealth. Where their Governours may be under ſome Government, and in Wrongs and Diſorders, they may have the Benefit of a Magiſtrate's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to appeal unto.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:63430:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1.</hi> The firſt Objection anſwered. <hi>2.</hi> The Government of a particular Church, hath Affinity with that of leſſer Bodies, more than with the Government of Empires and Kingdoms.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Object.</head>
                  <p n="1">§ 1. IT may be objected, that Churches are ſpiritual Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and of a more peculiar Conſideration, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Government; and therefore not to be reckoned with Civil, at leaſt not with Families, or ſuch mean and low Societies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Policy or Government in it ſelf, and all the ſorts of it, is from the Light of Nature, and common Reaſon. And this is generally ſuppoſed by all; that tho the Subject Matter, or Perſons governed, be of different kinds; yet the Law and Forms of Government may be the ſame where ſo appointed by Chriſt. And I rather inſiſt on ſuch a way of Diſcourſe and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, as moſt ſuitable to the Subject I am upon, but eſpecially becauſe Subordination of Churches to Churches is argued from the Light of Nature, and in this very Caſe, termed by our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren a Divine Topick. Now if we may argue and guide our ſelves in Church-Affairs by the Light that ſhineth forth (from the natural Wiſdom and Prudence of Man) in the Government and managing of Kingdoms; there is as much a <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> and ground of reaſoning from the Light that appears in the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Conſtitution and Government of any other civil Society.</p>
                  <p>I have mentioned in the Conſiderations, <hi>Cities, Families,</hi> and thoſe leſſer, and <hi>contained</hi> (as I term them) Societies or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations with particulars Churches: Becauſe I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Policy and Government of each (tho in other things different) to be more proportionable, and of greater Similitude in many things, then between particular Churches, and thoſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and <hi>containing</hi> Bodies, Kingdoms, Empires, or the like. Churches thus humbly conſtituted and governed, are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Civil Magiſtracy, of what Form ſoever the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth ſhall be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Confirmation of this Agreement or Similitude, I ſhall take for the moſt part the Conceſſions of the learned of each Perſwaſion. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances or Particulars are theſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:63430:22"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>§</hi> 2. 1. Families tho contained under the National Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where they are ſinuated, yet are intruſted with a ruling and governing Power compleat and ſufficient each in and for it ſelf; ſo are particular Churches.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>They are intruſted with a Government each for it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is not <hi>ſufficient</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi>) <hi>for a Church to have the preaching of the Word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Perk. <hi>on</hi> Rev. 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>but Church-Government. This Church</hi> (ſpeaking of <hi>Thyatira</hi>) <hi>is blamed becauſe ſhe did not uſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority God had given her.</hi> There is given to the Miniſters of each particular Congregation, according to Epiſcopal Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eſtabliſhed by our Law, not only a Power to preach, <hi>&amp;c. [Take Authority to preach the Word of God]</hi> but they are made <hi>Rectors,</hi> Governours in thoſe particular Churches, and it's ſaid to them, <hi>[Whoſe Sins thou doſt remit, they are remitted; and whoſe Sins thou doſt retain, they are retained]</hi> by which Words the Keys of Diſcipline are given them; ſee <hi>Bilſon</hi> Perpet. Govern. <hi>p.</hi> 213. <q>By Order of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>) all <hi>Presbyters</hi> are charged to <hi>adminiſter the Doctrine and Sacraments,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reduct. of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and the Difcipline of Chriſt as the Lord hath commanded, and as this Realm hath received the ſame.</hi> And that they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtand what the Lord hath commanded therein, the Exhortation of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> is appointed to be read unto them at the time of their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the Flock among whom the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers, to</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>ſo taken in</hi> Mat. 2.6. <hi>and</hi> Rev. 12.5. <hi>and</hi> 19.15. <hi>Ho. Eccl. Pol.</hi> lib. 3. Sect. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>rule the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, which he hath purchaſed with his Blood.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> tells us that for Preſervation of Chriſtianity there is not any thing more needful than that ſuch as are of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church have mutual Fellowſhip and Society one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. In which Conſideration the Catholick Church is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into anumber of diſtinct Societies, every of which is termed a Church within it ſelf, not an Aſſembly, but a Society, — A Church (as we are now to underſtand it) is a Society, that is, a number of Men belonging to ſome Chriſtian-Fellowſhip, the Place and Limits whereof are certain, having communion in the publick Exerciſe of ſuch Duties as are mentioned, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.47. As thoſe of the Myſtical Church by their inward Graces differ from all others which are not of the Body, and thoſe that are of the viſible Body of the Church, have the Notes of external Profeſſion. Even ſo theſe ſeveral Societies, or Churches, have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63430:22"/>
                        <hi>Properties</hi> belonging to them, as they are publick Chriſtian Societies. And of ſuch Properties, it may not be denied that one of the very <hi>chiefeſt</hi> is <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy.</hi> We uſe the name of Policy rather than Government, becauſe Church-Policy containeth both Government, and alſo whatſoever beſides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the ordering of the publick Affairs of the Church of God.</q> In which words he aſſerts not each particular Church to have Government in it ſelf; but this Government as a Property, or Propriety, by which it's diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Myſtical,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Catholick</hi> viſible Church. So that he doth not, as ſome of late, make the Catholick viſible Church the firſt Subject of the Keys; but each particular Society, or Church, ſuppoſing that great Body of Chriſtians to be only and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately under the Spiritual Government of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Compleat and ſufficient.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is not to be underſtood of ſuch a perfection, as may not with much advantage receive help both from the Power of the Magiſtrate, as I have ſhewed before, as alſo from the Counſel and Advice of other Churches: But I mean an eſſential Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatneſs or Sufficiency, not being deficient in any material re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for Government. This that learned Author expreſſeth in thoſe laſt Words: <hi>'We uſe the Word</hi> Policy, (ſaith he) <hi>rather than Government, becauſe Church-Policy containeth both Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alſo whatever beſides belongeth to the ordering of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church of God. Every particular Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Againſt <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt,</hi> lib 3, pag. 147.</note> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi>) <hi>having an Elderſhip, is a Catholick Church of Chriſt, under whom Paſtors, Doctors, and Elders are the miniſterial and immediate Governors.</hi> In which Words he intimateth a Compleatneſs in each particular Church for Government and Privileges, as much as if the Catholick viſible Church were Organical,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rutherf.</hi> Due Right or Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt. <hi>pag.</hi> 307.</note> and a gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Church. <q>The Power of Juriſdiction (ſaith one) is as perfect and compleat in one ſingle Congregation, as in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, as in a National, yea, as in the Catholick viſible Body.</q> 
                     <hi>All Things are yours,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to a particular Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Parker's</hi> Polit. lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> To this purpoſe Mr. <hi>Parker: Sicut non para,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As a particular Church is not a maimed or half, but a whole and perfect Body; ſo it is poſſeſſed with the whole and entire Church-Government, and not with a part only.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Oeconomick</hi> and Domeſtick Power is intrinſick and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to a Family,<note place="margin">2d Inſtance.</note> and is a Power derived immediatly from the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63430:23"/>Lord, by the Light of Nature, and hath not its original from any Power on Earth, Families being much more ancient than Common-Wealths: So Government or Diſcipline is intrinſick and inſeparable from the very Eſſence of a Church, received im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from Chriſt, and not the Grant or Conſtitution of any Secular Prince or State.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jackson</hi> of the Church, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. § 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Churches are endued</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi>) <hi>with a Judicature immediately derived from</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and independent upon any Earthly Power, or any Power whatſoever on Earth, whether Spiritual or Temporal.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bilſon</hi> of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prem. p. 171.</note> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> expreſſeth it thus: <hi>The Things compriſed in the Church, and by God himſelf commanded to the Church,</hi> (theſe Things are ſpecified in <hi>pag.</hi> 227. to be the <hi>Word, Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Keys,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power,</hi> and <hi>Cure of Souls</hi>) <hi>are ſubject to no mortal Creature, Pope, nor Prince.</hi> And thoſe of another Perſuaſion, are to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <q>The Church (ſaith Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi>) hath the Keys from Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Peaceable Plea,</hi> p. 300.</note> equally <hi>independent</hi> upon any mortal Man, in Diſcipline as in Doctrine.<note place="margin">Due Right of Presbyt <hi>cap.</hi> 9. § 9.</note> A Power and Right to Diſcipline, ſaith the ſame Author, is a Property eſſential to a Church, and is not removed from it, till God remove the Candleſtick, and the Church ceaſe to be a viſible Church.</q> 
                     <hi>Poteſtas ipſa de jure,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Power</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Ames</hi>) <hi>is ſo much the Right of a Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caſ. cen.</hi> lib 4. cap. 24. p. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>as it cannot be ſeparated, becauſe neceſſary, and immediatly floweth even from the Eſſence of each true Church.</hi> There are Authorities enow to be produced from the Writings of the Learned, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this particular. All grant there is a Government <hi>jure divino,</hi> (I ſpeak not of this or that Form) and by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of Jeſus Chriſt. It is denied by none but <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> and thoſe that follow him, who may as well deny Praying, Preaching, or Sacraments <hi>jure divino</hi> It is as expreſly ordained, that Diſcipline be exerciſed in the Name of Chriſt, as to preach, pray, or baptize in his Name. There are certainly <hi>Things of God,</hi> that are not the <hi>Things of Caeſar:</hi> And if thoſe Things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Chriſt hath put his Name, be not peculiarly his, I know not where we ſhall find the Joint. As we ſay, there were Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, ſo particular Churches, before any Commonwealths were, and Chriſtian Churches and Diſcipline exerciſed, many Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Emperors or Kings were Chriſtian: And therefore as Families have many Privileges ſo peculiar, and by the Law of Nature ſo much theirs, as are never touched or infringed by the Supreme Power of any Nation: So likewiſe it is with Churches,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63430:23"/>they have very many Privileges ſo evidently theirs, from the Law of Chriſt, and their ſpiritual Conſtitution, as Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates will do their utmoſt to preſerve and cheriſh, and not in the leaſt infringe. It is a part of <hi>Magna Charta: Conceſſimus Deo, &amp; hac preſenti Charta confirmavimus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>pro nobis &amp; Heredibus noſtris in perpetuum, quòd Eccleſia Anglicana libera ſit, &amp; habeat omnia jura ſua integra, &amp; Libertates ſuas illaeſas.</hi> And it is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Oath our Kings take at their Coronation, that <hi>He ſhall keep and maintain the lawful Rights and Liberties of the Holy Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A third Particular,<note place="margin">3d Inſtance.</note> or Inſtance of what we have ſuppoſed in the former <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> is this: The leſſer <hi>Corporations, Cities, Families,</hi> and the like, have not Authority or Juriſdiction one over another. It is the ſame with <hi>Churches,</hi> each having the Fountain and Original of their own Power (as before is ſhewed) immediatly proceeding from Chriſt in themſelves, and not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, or one from another; cannot by any Art or Device of Man be made to riſe up above it ſelf, as it doth, if one Church exerciſeth a Power or Juriſdiction over another. There is no Invention of Man, that by contriving Pipes, or any other Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, can make Water freely and naturally run higher than the Spring-Head. Tho that Juriſdiction which hath its riſe in a particular Church, be pumped up into a <hi>Claſſis</hi> or Synod, it is but the ſame it was before. <hi>Synods,</hi> ſaith <hi>Parker</hi> out of <hi>Chamier,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Polit lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13 § 9.</hi> Diſp de Polit. Eccleſ. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>nullam habeant Authoritatem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They have no Authority but what is derived from particular Churches.</hi> So <hi>Voetius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There ſeems to be a great Emphaſis in thoſe Particles of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, <hi>Children obey your Parents,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; ſo to Servants:<note place="margin">1 pheſ. 6.1.</note> And ſpeaking of the Relation of Husbands and Wives, by which is ſet forth our Obedience to Chriſt and his Officers, it is more appropriate, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.24. <hi>As the Church is ſubject to Chriſt, ſo let the Wives be to their own Husbands;</hi> it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>propriis viris,</hi> not only <hi>theirs, but their own Husbands.</hi> It is ſaid, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4. <hi>One that ruleth well his own Houſe,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. So of Miniſters, <hi>Know them that labour among you,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>and are ever you in the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.12. and in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Duces veſtri,</hi> your Captains, Officers in Churches, being as exactly limited, as in an Army. There is no Power in a Superior to command, where no Obligation upon the Inferior to obey. And therefore the Lord ſeems by theſe Expreſſions,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63430:24"/>to limit both Church and Family-Power within their own Walls.</p>
                  <p>This is the Judgment of the Learned of each Perſuaſion. Biſhop <hi>Davenant. Nota eſt Juriſconſultorum regula, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <q>It is a known Rule of Lawyers, A Sentence given by him that is not his Judg, is void in Law. But particular Churches are not the Judges of private Perſons that are of other Churches, how much leſs then over the Churches themſelves; ſuch Sentences were to be ſlighted and contemned, as of a Judg that preſumeth to make Laws out of the bounds of his own Juriſdiction.</q> 
                     <hi>Nec poteſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De judice cont.</hi> cap. 16. p. 90.</note> 
                     <hi>nec debet</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author elſewhere) <hi>particularis una Eccleſia judiciaria authoritate aliam ſibi non ſubjectam a Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca abſcindere, quaelibet enim Eccleſia filios ſuos ad conſenſionem in Doctrina publicè ſtabilita cenſuris adigit. Sed fratres Eccleſiarum externarum monet pro officio charitatis, non punit pro imperio poteſtatis.</hi> Dr. <hi>Field,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Of the <hi>Church</hi> lib 5.</note> as a common Reſolution of Divines, tells us, <hi>That if a Biſhop ventures to do any Act of Juriſdiction out of his own Dioceſs,</hi> (that is, his particular Church, ſo <hi>cap.</hi> 30.) <hi>as to excommunicate or abſolve, or the like, all ſuch Acts are utterly void, and of no force.</hi> The ſame thing, ſaith Dr. <hi>Crakanthorp, cont. Spal. cap.</hi> 28. <hi>pag.</hi> 177.<note place="margin">Jue divinum Regim. <hi>p. 230.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <q>Every Congregation (ſay our Brethren) hath equal Power one as much as another, according to the trite and known Axiom, <hi>Par in parem non habet imperium,</hi> An Equal hath no Power over an Equal.</q> 
                     <hi>Eccleſiae inſtitutae parochiales integrae ſunt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Diſp. de Polit. Eccleſ. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>inter ſe collaterales, &amp; poteſtate Eccleſiaſtica aequales,</hi> ſaith <hi>Voetius.</hi> Which you may Engliſh out of the Engliſh Puritaniſm thus: <q>Particular Churches are in all Matters equal, and are entruſted by Chriſt with the ſame Eccleſiaſtical Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</q>
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 2. § 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Jewel, Reynolds, Whitaker,</hi> and moſt of our Divines, againſt the Papiſts, are large in their Diſputes for a parity of Churches, and Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> hath written a whole Chapter <hi>de pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccleſiarum.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Polit lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </note> Some make a particular Church to be of larger Extenſion, as a Dioceſs, a Province, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that altereth not the State of the Queſtion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="digression">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63430:24"/>
               <head>A DIGRESSION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Of Independentiſm, Name and Thing. <hi>2.</hi> Its conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency with the Kings Supremacy.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THis State of a particular Church, namely, their equality in reſpect of Juriſdiction or coercive Power one over another, was wont to be expreſſed by INDEPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENCY, which though now it be a term of Raproach, yet formerly made uſe of by good Authors, as very fit and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, to ſet forth this Priviledge of each particular Church compleat and intire: namely, their not Dependency or Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the Juriſdiction of another Church, as their Head and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> in his learned Treatiſe of the <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>15.</hi> Cap. <hi>119.</hi>
                  </note> uſeth this term frequently, <q>Unity (ſaith he in one place) of Diſcipline, or of INDEPENDENT Judicature, is eſſential and neceſſary to the Church, as viſible. Hence there be as many diſtinct vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churches, as there be INDEPENDENT Judicatures Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick.</q> Dr. <hi>Sibbs</hi> thus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Goſpel-anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> pag. 94.</note> 
                  <q>Particular viſible Churches are now God's Tabernacle. The Church of the Jews was a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, but now God hath erected particular Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles. Every particular Church under one Paſtor is the Church of God, a ſeveral Church INDEPENDENT. The Church of <hi>England</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author) is called a particular Church from other Nations, becauſe it is under a Government Civil, which is not dependent on any other Foreign Prince.</q> 
                  <hi>Each Church,</hi> ſaith <hi>Voctius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deſp. Cau. Pap. lib. 3. § 3. c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>as it hath its proper Form of an Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Body or Society, ſo its endued with its proper Government and Juriſdiction; which it exerciſeth DEPENDENTLY upon Chriſt, his Word and Spirit, but INDEPENDENTLY in reſpect of all other Churches.</hi> Mr. <hi>Bates,</hi> 
                  <q>One Company of Men aſſembled,<note place="margin">Treatiſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Anno 1613.</note> hath no Authority to impoſe things upon many Churches. 1. None now have Apoſtolick Authority. 2. Each Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a Body INDEPENDENT of any Eccleſiaſtical Power. There is no Ordinance of God for this, (ſaith Mr. <hi>Banes</hi>) that Churches within a circuit ſhould be tyed to a certain Head-Church for Government, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. and <hi>pag.</hi> 13. We affirm that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63430:25"/>no ſuch Head-Church was ordained either vertually, or actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but that all Churches were ſingle Congregations, equal, INDEPENDENT each of other in regard of Subjection.</q> 
                  <hi>Every true Church</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>now is an INDEPENDENT Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Collection of ſundry matters, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1601.</note> and in another place, <hi>The Congregational Body Politick ſpiritually INDEPENDENT, is Chriſt's Divine Ordinance in the Goſpel.</hi> 
                  <q>One ordinary Congregation of Chriſtians, is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Body Politick INDEPENDENT. That is, it hath the Right and Power of ſpiritual Adminiſtration and Government in it ſelf,<note place="margin">Confeſſion of Faith, p. Anno 1601.</note> and over it ſelf, by the common and free conſent of the People, INDEPENDENTLY and immediately under Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This was the Opinion generally of N. Conformiſts, as is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by one of themſelves in the Name of the reſt, as alſo by <hi>B. Downam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sermon at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> p. 5.</note> 
                  <q>They (that is the N. C.) ſay, that every Pariſh by Right, hath ſufficient Authority within it ſelf, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly derived from Chriſt, for the Government of it ſelf in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical. To the Pariſhional Presbytery conſiſting of their Pariſh-Biſhop and his Elders, they do aſcribe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, immediate, and independent Authority for Eccleſiaſtical Government for every proper viſible Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Independency</hi> of Churches was aſſerted (by thoſe learned men of a former Age) in relation only to a ſuperior Church-power properly <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and ſuch as is claimed <hi>jure divino;</hi> and not in relation to that Eccleſiaſtical Power which is in, or exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from, the Civil Magiſtrate. Some of them have thus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed a particular Church; It's <hi>a Body Politick ſpiritually indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> or <hi>independent</hi> in relation to a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Superiority: which is expreſſed fully, by him that wrote <hi>Church-Government with the Peoples conſent,</hi> pag. 115. <q>Though we affirm the Church-Government is <hi>independent,</hi> and immediately derived from Chriſt; yet we affirm alſo, that the Civil Magiſtrate is even therein (that is, in Eccleſiaſtical Matters) Supreme Governor civilly. And though nothing may be impoſed on the Chriſtian Churches againſt their Will, by any <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Authority (for ſo only we intend) yet we affirm withall, that the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may impoſe on them ſpiritual Matters, by Civil Power, yea, whether they like or diſlike, if it be good in his Eyes, that is, if he judge it within his Commiſſion from God.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:63430:25"/>
               <p>And ſuch an <hi>Independency</hi> hath been pleaded for alſo, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued by them to be much more <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with His Majeſties Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, than a DEPENDENCY or <hi>Subordination</hi> of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to any ſpiritual Power. And it was their profeſſed Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, That no External Power ought to be exerciſed in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Matters, any where (within that ſpace betwixt a particular Congregation inſtituted by Chriſt, and the Catholick Viſible Church) by any perſon but the Civil Magiſtrate, or by his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
               <p>Take their own Words. <hi>They that make claim</hi> Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino, <hi>of Power and Juriſdiction to meddle with other Churches, than that one Congregation of which they are Members, do uſurp upon the Supremacy of the Civil Magiſtrate, who alone hath, and ought to have a power of Juriſdiction over the ſeveral Congregations in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,</hi> &amp;c. A Proteſtation of the King's Supremacy made and publiſhed in <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. <hi>§.</hi> 27. and in <hi>§.</hi> 28. <q>The King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is to be General Overſeer of all the Churches within his Dominions, and ought o employ under him, fit perſons to overſee the Churches in their ſeveral Diviſions, <hi>viſiting</hi> them, and puniſhing whatſoever is amiſs in any of them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bradſhew</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation,</hi> againſt <hi>Johnſon,</hi> writes thus: <hi>It's their principal Honour</hi> (ſpeaking of Archbiſhops and Biſhops) <hi>to be Commiſſioners and Viſitors in Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Eccleſiaſtical under the King, over the Paſtors and Churches of Provinces and Dioceſſes.</hi> In his Anſwer to <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s <hi>firſt Reaſon:</hi> And in his Anſwer to his <hi>ſecond.</hi> He queſtions him thus: <q>1. Whether the Supreme Magiſtrate hath not Power to overſee and govern all the ſeveral Churches within his Dominion, yea, whether he be not bound ſo to do. 2. Whether for his further help and aſſiſtance herein, he may not make choice of grave, learned, and reverent men, to aſſiſt him in the ſame Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 3 Whether by vertue of his Power theſe perſons thus called, to aſſiſt the Supreme Magiſtrate, may not lawfully try the Gifts of Miniſters within his Dominions, convent them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, examine how they have behaved themſelves in their places, and puniſh the blame-worthy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In a Petition alſo to King <hi>James</hi> for <hi>Tolleration,</hi> 
                  <q>That your Highneſs would afford us, and aſſign to us ſome perſons qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with Wiſdom, Learning and Vertue, to be under your
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63430:26"/>Highneſs our Overſeers, for our more peaceable orderly and dutiful carriage of our ſelves, both in our worſhiping God, and in all other our Affairs, at your pleaſure. To whom with all Readineſs and Subjection we are willing to be accomptable and anſwerable, always.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The opinions of learned men about Church Matters (Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſpecially) were collected together, in a Treatiſe which was put into <hi>Latin</hi> by Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> and in an Epiſtle of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, avouched by him (who was a man much ſtudied in thoſe Controverſies) to be the Judgment of <hi>Cartwright, Fenner, Fulk, Whitaker, Rainolds, Perkins, Brightman,</hi> and thoſe that were more Ancient: As <hi>Wichliff, Tyndal, Rogers, Bradford, Gilby, Fox, Moore, Dearing, Noel, Greenham, Dogmata iſta,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe Tenents (ſaith he) were either their Principles, or ſo conjunct with them, as not to be denied, theirs. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> (ſaith the Author) <hi>hath not ſubjected any Church or Congregation of his to any other Superior Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, than unto that which is within it ſelf — the Civil Magiſtrate alone upon Earth, hath power to puniſh a whole Church or Congregation,</hi> Cap. 2. <hi>§.</hi> 3. and more fully in <hi>§.</hi> 12. <q>They hold and believe (ſaith he) that the <hi>Equality</hi> in Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction and Authority, of Churches and Church Miniſters, is no more derogatory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the State and Glory of a Monarch, than the parity or equality of <hi>School-maſters</hi> of ſeveral Schools, or <hi>Maſters</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Families.</hi> Yea, they hold the clean contrary, that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality</hi> of Churches and Church Officers in Eccleſiaſtical Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and Authority, was that principally that advanced Antichriſt unto his Throne, and brought the Kings and Princes of the Earth unto ſuch vaſſalage under him. And that the Civil Authority, and Glory of Secular Princes and States, hath ever decayed and withered, the more that Eccleſiaſtical Officers of the Church, have been advanced and ſet up in Authority beyond the limits and confines, that Chriſt in his Word hath preſcribed unto them.</q> And in Cap. 6. <hi>§.</hi> 6. They are ſaid to <hi>deny a principal part of the Kings Supremacy,</hi> that hold any Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or Offices over Churches <hi>jure divino, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> will and pleaſure of the King and Civil States of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from what is ſaid, cap. 5. <hi>§.</hi> 12. It is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that this way is as little prejudicial to the Subjects <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly there ſaid, <hi>If any Member of a Congregation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:63430:26"/>crime, ſhall of himſelf forſake Communion with the Church, that then the Eccleſiaſtical Officers, have no authority, or juriſdiction over him, but only the Civil Magiſtrate, Parents, or Maſters,</hi> &amp;c. So that as perſons are free (otherwiſe than from conſcience of duty) to <hi>joyn</hi> with theſe Aſſemblies, ſo alſo to <hi>leave</hi> them, remaining al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways under the Magiſtrates Eccleſiaſticul power and care.</p>
               <p>I have made this Digreſſion, not only for the matters ſake, which is very ſutable to our preſent Subject, but alſo to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the <hi>Congregational</hi> way. 1. That it is not ſuch a <hi>Novelty</hi> as is pretended. This of the <hi>equality</hi> of Churches, and thence an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency</hi> (from which we are reproachfully ſurnamed) ſeems to be the worſt of our Tenents: Yet it appears to be no other, but what the reverend and learned of a former age have aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Nor do I know any other of their opinions or practices, but may as eaſily be remonſtrated, to be the aſſertions of thoſe holy men. Nor ſecondly, inconſiſtent with civil Magiſtracy, or with their Power in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs. And as a further Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony hereof, they take the Oaths both of <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</hi> Profeſſedly aſſent alſo to <q>All the Articles of Religion which concern only the Confeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrin of the Sacraments, compriſed in a Book enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Articles whereupon it was agreed by the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the whole Clergy in the Convocation Anno</hi> 1562. <hi>for the avoiding of diverſity of Opinions, and for the eſtabliſhing of conſent touching true Religion,</hi>
                  </q> as is required by Stat. 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 12. And do humbly hope, living peaceably under his Majeſties Government, they ſhall obtain their ſhare in that Indulgence his Majeſty graciouſly purpoſed to ſhew to ſuch perſons, as through want of full ſatisfaction, differ in ſmaller matters from the preſent Eſtabliſhment.</p>
               <p>A fourth Particular, which ariſeth from the former,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Inſtance.</note> is this. Families being not ſubordinate one to another, they cannot aſſociate or unite into any large or great Body; and therefore do, and may more conveniently retain their Government (though it be <hi>peculiar</hi> and <hi>diſtinct</hi>) in any Common-wealth, of what form ſoever, without prejudice to the Peace and Welfare of it. So is it with Churches, their State and Government (as it is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt) is ſuch, as is conſiſtent with, and no prejudice unto any civil Powers under whom they are ſituated. And that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:63430:27"/>upon this account principally: Having no <hi>Dependency</hi> in Reſpect of Power or Juriſdiction one on another, they cannot in their own Sphere enlarge themſelves by Subordinations, to a political Body of any ſuch Extenſion and Greatneſs, as may render their Obedience or Compliance more doubtful or uncertain. It is matter of Jealouſie with Princes and States, when there is in their Dominions a Body, large and extenſive, firmly joyned and compact in it ſelf, of an intereſt peculiar and not holding of them. Particular Churches are of a ſmall compaſs, ſometimes compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in <hi>One,</hi> ordinarily but of a few Families. So that in this reſpect, though their Intereſt and Government be peculiar, they may retain it, and for ſubſtance the ſame (as Families do) throughout the World. Which will further appear in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is granted on all hands, That the Lord hath limited his Church to a Government which is perpetual, and for ſubſtance to be the ſame in all places. As alſo that the Nations, from their Civil Government variouſly, and as they judge moſt prudent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since the <hi>Wall of partition</hi> by Chriſts Death was broken down: The Goſpel and Chriſtian Churches were by Chriſts commiſſion to be planted in all parts of the World. It ſtands therefore with common reaſon, that the Church Government Chriſt hath left us, is of that Nature, as without any ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Alteration may comply with, and not be prejudicial to, any Civil Government.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If particular Churches by Union become one body, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention as large as the Civil State, There will hardly be a due and peaceable accord, and each enjoy its priviledge and Liberties without prejudice to the other; unleſs theſe two great bodies be moulded and formed one with reſpect unto the other. The policy therefore of the <hi>Nation</hi> and the National <hi>Church</hi> of the Jewes, were both reſpectively formed by the Lord himſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence this opinion of <hi>States-men,</hi> that there is no form of Church Government left by Chriſt, or his Apoſtles; but to be moulded by the wiſdom and diſcretion of Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as <hi>may beſt ſute and joynt in</hi> with the Civil Government. And of <hi>others</hi> the contrary, <q>The Commonwealth (ſaith one) muſt be made to agree with the Church, and the Government, thereof with her Government: for as the <hi>Houſe</hi> is before the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:63430:27"/>
                     <hi>Hangings,</hi> therefore the Hangings which came after, muſt be framed to the Houſe which was before: ſo the Church being before there was any <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and the Commonwealth coming after, muſt be faſhioned and made ſuitable to the Church: We need none of theſe extteams.</q> The middle way is this, Let not the Churches claim to be National or Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <hi>Jure divino,</hi> but leave ſuch diſpoſements to the civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and be numbred with thoſe leſſer Societies, Families, Cities, Colledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For theſe do retain in themſelves much the ſame form of Government and Freedom therein throughout the World.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is not ſo much a different Form of Government: For in each Republick there are contained leſſer Societies of all Forms; but their <hi>Extention</hi> and <hi>Potency</hi> in numerouſneſs of Perſons, by which they are made up. Nor from this Principallity, but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Incorporation</hi> begets the Jealouſies. If parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches become <hi>Dioceſan, Provincial,</hi> or <hi>National</hi> by Union from the Law, or Direction of the Civil Magiſtrate, for the better exerciſe of that Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, the Lord hath intruſted him with, and <hi>conveniency</hi> of ſuch perſons as he ſhall appoint to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Churches; in ſuch a caſe the Greatneſs of <hi>Churches</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be diſturbent to the Civil Government, being ſo directly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its cognizance.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Holy Common-wealth,</hi> R. B. <hi>p.</hi> 2. 220.</note> 
                  <hi>The Common-wealth</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>containeth all the people in a whole Nation or more, united in one Soveraign, but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches (diſtinct from the univerſal united in Chriſt) have no general Eccleſiaſtical Officers, in whom a Nation muſt</hi> Unite <hi>as one Church.</hi> How then become they to be termed a National Church? Anſ. <hi>As ſeveral Corporations in one Kingdom, or as ſo many Schools that have a peculiar form of Government, but ſuch only as is under</hi> (and united in) <hi>the Magiſtrates Government in its kind.</hi> If this ſhould be claimed as the Law or Priviledge of each Family, that the Governors, be it the Father, or Husband, or Maſter, are thereby inveſted by Nature with the ſame Power, in reſpect to all Families in a Nation; and by ſeveral Correſpondencies and Subordinations raiſe, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite</hi> themſelves at laſt into a general Aſſembly or Repreſentative. And by Vertue of that <hi>Enconomical</hi> Authority give Laws to the whole Nation, though not as their <hi>Subjects;</hi> yet to the ſame perſons under another notion, that is, as <hi>Wives, Children, Servants.</hi> There is no well Governed State could entertain ſuch a ſpreading intereſt as this, without great
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:63430:28"/>doubtfulneſs, leſt their Authority and Supremacy, ſhould hereby be much Ecclipſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But a particular Church conſiſting only of a few perſons in it ſelf, and independent on others; is neceſſitated to depend, under God, upon the Magiſtrate for protection. Which if they ſhould not obtain, but be oppoſed and perſecuted; yet have no ability to reſiſt, being as a Family ſingle and alone, not able to defend it ſelf or moleſt others. Nor if they were able, is it lawful for a Church to compel by the <hi>Sword,</hi> more than the Magiſtrate may by <hi>the Keyes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. with 24, 25.</note> or what is peculiar to the ſacred Function. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> erred in the latter, and <hi>Peter</hi> in the former. The primitive rule and practice was this, being <hi>perſecuted in one City</hi> to <hi>fly into another,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> that <hi>their flight may not be in the Winter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23.24.20.</note> No nor do we judg that theſe ſpiritual weapons (the Keyes or Cenſures) may lawfully by a Church, or any Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly be threatned, or drawn forth againſt a whole Nation, and the chief Governors thereof, to urge or compel, eſpecially in State concernment (as the <hi>Pope</hi> and ſome <hi>others</hi> have done) though it be truly <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth <hi>Inſtance</hi> or <hi>particular</hi> is this.<note place="margin">The <hi>5.</hi> Inſtance.</note> A Family of all Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations or Societies, is the loweſt ſpecies or kind, it's <hi>Conſociatio ſimplex &amp; prima,</hi> and hath the leaſt of pomp or ſtate in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it. Cottages are built low, Palaces with many ſtories one above another. Thoſe great and extenſive Bodies <hi>Empires</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> repreſent in their <hi>Government</hi> more ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatly the <hi>myſtical</hi> Church, in reſpect to Jeſus Chriſt who is their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> whoſe Kingdom is with <hi>Power and Glory,</hi> a Power that is truly Imperial and Princely, having Officers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him (his Kingdom reaching to the utmoſt ends of the Earth) who <hi>in his name</hi> command reward, and puniſh. But <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular</hi> Churches as Governed by his Miniſters, have their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion rather with the meaneſt and loweſt Societies of men.</p>
               <p>The Scripture ſeems to point at more than a ſimilitude and likeneſs betwixt a Family and Church, in the managing of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; I mean in the general, and what is it not determined by expreſs Inſtitution. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Timothy</hi> about Church affairs, mentioneth their expertneſs in Governing a <hi>Family,</hi> as a good preparative or qualification for <hi>Church</hi> adminiſtrations. And this is not only <hi>Negatively,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>if a man know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care over the Church of God.</hi> But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatively,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:63430:28"/>
                  <hi>Theſe things I writ, that thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God,</hi> The ſence is full in thoſe words,<note place="margin">verſ. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Church of the living God,</hi> yet it is added <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> purpoſed as it were to carry the Eye back to what was written, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. which ſheweth that there is a great <hi>affinity</hi> betwixt our Houſes and the Houſhold of God. <hi>In a Fathers Governing his Children</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>there is a lively reſemblance of ſuch Duties of Government, which he is to diſpence towards the Church. There is nothing enjoyned, the Miniſter as a Father of Children, which belongeth not to him as he is a ſpiritual Father of the Children of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the other hand, it may be obſerved, this queſtion being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.1:</note> who or <hi>which of us ſhall be the greateſt in the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> upon ſuppoſition (the Church being ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a <hi>Kingdom</hi>) there would be places of State, and higher dignity in it, as are in the Kingdoms of the World. Chriſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers: There ſhall be no ſuch thing, no primacy in one Apoſtle over another, no, <hi>the greateſt of you ſhall be the leaſt,</hi> and the <hi>firſt ſhall be the laſt,</hi> Though a Jurisdiction and power truly <hi>Imperial,</hi> abſolute, and equal to any of the <hi>Kings of the Gentiles,</hi> belongs to me, and I exerciſe it in thoſe ſpiritual adminiſtrations, yet no ſuch dignity may be aſſumed by you, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When the Scripture ſpeaks of a particular Church under the notion of a <hi>Family</hi> or Houſhold, Government or <hi>Ruling</hi> is mentioned as that wherein the ſimilitude or proportion is moſt perſpicuous and clear, as hath been ſhewed: But ſpeaking here of a Church under this expreſſion, <hi>a Kingdom,</hi> how purpoſely are we cautioned againſt an imitation in Rule and Authority?</p>
               <p n="2">2. We may further obſerve that Ambition after greatneſs in thoſe that manage theſe <hi>great things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> is an infirmity almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable. For if 1. Such perſons, the holieſt men on the earth, they who had <hi>forſaken all to follow</hi> Chriſt. 2. And theſe ſo often relapſe into this folly after they had been reduced from it by Chriſt. 3. And at ſuch times, immediatly after Chriſt had minded them of his Death,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.19, 20. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.21, 24. &amp; 19. with 24.</note> and that <hi>one</hi> of them ſhould <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him,</hi> when alſo they had newly been at the Communion with him: What great cauſe is there that every man be very jealous of his own heart?</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is not unevident alſo from the Diſciples often Diſputes about their greatneſs; that moſt of our controverſies and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:63430:29"/>about Church-Government, if traced home, will be found to ariſe from hence, namely: The having our Eye fixed ſo much upon the <hi>lofty</hi> ſtate of a <hi>Kingdom</hi> as our pattern in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements, rather than that familiar and <hi>humble</hi> way of a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi> For indeed this was the only breach and conteſt that we read of, amongſt thoſe holy Men, the Diſciples of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And where ſuch differences are, a Reconcilement will be found more difficult, becauſe where the mind is bent on worldly greatneſs, we are very dull and ſlow in underſtanding whatſoever ſhall be ſpoken (though from Chriſt himſelf) that ſeems to croſs thoſe thoughts; as appears alſo in that ſtory, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.32.</p>
               <p>A Parent or Maſter would not eaſily have been tempted into ſuch an Error, or make this queſtion, who or which of us ſhall be the greateſt? that is, have a paternal power over other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and their Families, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And had the Diſciples looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Miniſterial</hi> power under ſo low and humble a notion as what is <hi>Economical, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> would never have thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous, that they ſhould have an Apoſtolical power over the other Apoſtles, <hi>Hoc Papatum fefellit,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith <hi>Cartw.</hi>) <hi>This deceived the Papacy, which governs throughout after the form of worldly</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Plurimorum conſenſu Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia. à repub. formam illam magna parte mutuata eſt Eileſac.</note> 
                  <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires. The Pope he is as the Emperor himſelf, the Cardinals as his Deligates or Repreſentative, the Arch-Biſhops as the Governors of Provinces,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hence</hi> John <hi>calls the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>the Image of the Beaſt, the Vizard of the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For further confirmation of this fifth particular or Inſtance, let it be conſidered, how ſeldom and ſparingly a particular Church in the N. T. is termed a <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Although 1. Its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be derived as a Branch of Chriſts <hi>Kingly</hi> Office. 2. Church Ordinances are the moſt effectual means by which he exerciſeth his ſpiritual <hi>Soveraignty</hi> in each mans ſoul. 3. His <hi>Myſtical Kingdom</hi> on earth, thus by parcels, comes to be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under an external ſpiritual regiment, and 4. His Church when National was managed in the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Yet notwithſtanding all theſe leading occaſions, how ſparingly, and not without ſpecial Caution is a particular Church thus termed? Whereas not only the <hi>Society,</hi> but the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Officers, Ordinances, Cenſures, and other Church matters, are univerſally and frequently delivered unto us by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in terms apt to mind us of this low and humble policy. To give ſome Inſtances thereof.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:63430:29"/>
               <p n="1">1. A particular Church or the Society it ſelf, is repreſented unto us as the <hi>Houſe of the living God,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. <hi>His Houſhold,</hi> Matth. 24, 45. over which he hath ſet <hi>Rulers</hi> (therefore to be underſtood of a particular Church, for the univerſal is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately under the rule of Chriſt.) A <hi>Brotherhood,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. and the Members of it <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi> (as the Paſtors <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.2. and it is given as a title of Dignity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1, 23. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.12. yea to the <hi>Poor</hi> as well as to the <hi>Rich,</hi> and to thoſe of <hi>low</hi> as <hi>high</hi> degree, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Church Ordinances as 1.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16.</note> By <hi>teaching</hi> and admoniſhing the <hi>Word</hi> is ſaid to <hi>dwell amongſt them</hi> in all Wiſdom <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.45. The <hi>faithful and wiſe Ruler</hi> of Chriſts Houſhold <hi>is to give them meat in due ſeaſon.</hi> It is a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Paſtors duty, who is hereby admoniſhed to <hi>feed with knowledge,</hi> and to be much in it, that the Family may be <hi>richly</hi> and plentifully, and not ſparingly, niggardly fed. The <hi>Word dwelling,</hi> is the Houſhold Bread or Food, which by the <hi>Stewards</hi> or Miniſters is to be <hi>rightly divided,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. and reſpectively diſpenſed as <hi>milk to the Babes</hi> in the Family, and <hi>ſtrong meat</hi> to others, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.13, 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. 2. The <hi>Sacrament</hi> an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance peculiar to this Society, it's repreſented unto us as the <hi>Supper of the Lord,</hi> a Spiritual repaſt of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine.</hi> It came in the place of a Family Ordinance the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and ſo termed: Churches being now become Gods Family, and the Lords <hi>Supper</hi> their <hi>Feaſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.8. but moſt to our purpoſe, are ſuch expreſſions as ſet forth the Governours and Diſcipline appointed to a particular Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Officers</hi> are as the <hi>Stewards and Servants</hi> in this Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and ſo termed not in relation to <hi>Chriſt</hi> only, who is the <hi>Lord,</hi> but to the <hi>Church</hi> his Family.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1.</note> Chriſt abates of the over-high expectations of his Diſciples, by telling them that thoſe who are the chiefeſt amongſt them, ought to be even as <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> in the Houſe, that attend at the Table, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.26, 27. There were thoſe in <hi>Corinth</hi> raiſed much above their level (whom <hi>Paul</hi> perſonates in himſelf and <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Cephas</hi>) even equal with Chriſt, as having the Fountain of their excellency in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 13. with 4.6.</note> and communicated unto others of their own (as great Princes and <hi>Benefactors</hi>) like Chriſt:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> this being Lordly and Princely, <hi>Paul</hi> tells them, they <hi>raigned like Kings.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> To reduce from
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:63430:30"/>this exorbitant height to a juſt ballance, <hi>Paul</hi> ſets down the rate they may value themſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us, as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, Stewards of the Myſteries of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſures,</hi> the <hi>Keyes</hi> that open and ſhut; this expreſſion hath its reference to a Houſe or City moſt properly. And in the firſt place, particularly the Cenſure of <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> which is as the <hi>purging out of the old leaven,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7, 13. this was done by a careful and diligent ſearch into every corner of the houſe.<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> So the Excommunicate perſon, like <hi>Cain,</hi> is caſt out of the Family, and droven from <hi>the preſence of God.</hi> With ſuch a one <hi>not to eat,</hi> is all one with holding him as a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and Publican.</hi> This Cenſure is temed a <hi>Rod,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the Correction of our Children is termed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</note> Diſcipline, ſee <hi>Beza.</hi> The Apoſtles being Spiritual Parents, <hi>threaten</hi> the <hi>Rod,</hi> that is to cenſure in a Diſcipline way, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>In the mouth of two or three Witneſſes,</hi> &amp;c. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. And then <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>If I come again I will not ſpare,</hi> which is the ſame with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21. <hi>Shall I come with a</hi> Rod?</p>
               <p>The ſixth <hi>Inſtance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>6</hi> Inſtance.</note> As the Government of a Family is low and humble, ſo it is carried on in the moſt familiar and affectionate way; there is an intimacy, and daily converſe with our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>Correction</hi> are much ſweetned from that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care and Affection, we have experienced in <hi>other</hi> dealings. It is thus with Churches; though the Power there exerciſed, be ſome way coercive, yet brotherly, and ſubmitted unto with much Reverence, being adminiſtred by thoſe we love, honour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon,<note place="margin">Prop. to the Gen. Aſſem. <hi>1647.</hi>
                  </note> as Spiritual Fathers. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Power</hi> (ſaith our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi>) <hi>is indeed furniſhed with Authority, yet that Authority is rather the Fatherly, than the Kingly Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have ſaid that neither the cenſures of the Church, nor of civil Magiſtrate, <hi>morally</hi> work upon us further than we work upon our ſelves. Yet there is this difference, the weapons of the one being carnal, affect the ſenſes, and by them the mind coming in upon it more ſuddenly and ſtrongly. <hi>Senſe</hi> and Appetite have now a broad, ready, and more direct way to the Soul than <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But Church-cenſures touch us not, or very little in any Bodily concernment. So that nothing comes in upon us any way, but what we our ſelves are willing to let in. It is a great advantage therefore, and much to our Edification, that the perſons who deal with us in ſuch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:63430:30"/>a way, be firſt let into us, that is, much in our affections and good opinion, and having entertained the perſons, their miniſtration will the eaſier be let in with them, and ſo we come to be <hi>taken by Craft,</hi> as it were, (as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. that is, we are induced by a ſweet and attractive Bait, to take our ſelves. The Perſons therefore that are over us in the Lord, being ſuch as we intimately know, and daily converſe with, ſuch as our ſelves have choſen to be our ſpiritual Fathers, ſuch alſo as we have experienced their goodneſs and tenderneſs in other Goſpel-Adminiſtrations: we more eaſily ſubject to their Rebukes and Cenſures, as coming from the ſame Affection. The Ruling power in a Family, is you know by thoſe that are intimately known, and greatly oblige, as Parents who daily care and provide for us for preſent and to come, and therefore though they correct us, yea, ſometimes in <hi>Paſſion,</hi> yet <hi>we give them reverence,</hi> Hebr. 12.9. Cenſures in Churches, or Church-Chaſtiſements, <hi>are</hi> therefore or <hi>ought</hi> to be from thoſe that inſtruct and give us our portion in ſpiritual Comforts: the Rulers of Chriſt's Houſhold gives them <hi>their meat in due ſeaſon. We exhorted and comforted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 24.45. 1 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and charged every one of them, as a Father doth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Paul</hi> can <hi>charge</hi> them, and with greater Authority, even in their own hearts who have had experience, how in a Fatherly way, he <hi>Exhorts, Comforts,</hi> and <hi>Travels</hi> as it were <hi>in Birth with them.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> urgeth Obedience and Submiſſion upon ſuch a Conſideration, <hi>Obey them that have Rule over you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſubmit your ſelves; for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi> That is, there is an intimate and affectionate relation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and you, being ſuch, as Faſt, and Pray, and Mourn, and Rejoyce, yea, Eat and Drink with you daily at the ſame Table of the Lord, and are intruſted with the Care of your Souls from the hand of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This cannot be where the Paſtoral or Miniſterial Work is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the <hi>Keys</hi> of the Church hung apart. Thoſe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us not, nay, are <hi>Strangers</hi> to us, <hi>Rule over us;</hi> Rebukes and Chaſtiſements in this ſpiritual way, are from thoſe whoſe Faces we never ſaw, or know ſo much as by name. It's true, we may argue thus, They are ſtrangers, expect no favour therefore, or mercy from them, if you offend: this procures Obedience indeed, but it is in a ſervile way. The mind of Chriſt is, that as our Submiſſion to himſelf, ſo to his Miniſters (who even in Cenſures
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63430:31"/>act in his Name) be affectionate, filial, and drawn by the cords of love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus have I gone through with the</hi> Inſtances <hi>promiſed, with what brevity the nature of the matter would permit. By which it is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to parallel theſe</hi> Societies <hi>in reſpect to the intrinſick Form of Government</hi> peculiar to each: <hi>(for that, in a Church is from the Inſtitution of Chriſt, rather than the light of Nature) but the more</hi> general <hi>ſtate and habitude of Eccleſiaſtical Government as Churches ſtand diſpoſed to the Civil Magiſtrate, or one to another, and what the light of Nature and common Reaſon contribute hereunto, being ſo much inſiſted upon. What hath been ſaid, I hope tends to</hi> Union <hi>and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation. Thoſe that hold</hi> any <hi>ſpiritual Government</hi> Jure Divino, <hi>and by the appointment of Jeſus Chriſt, do not deny it to a particular Church: And thoſe that hold</hi> none, <hi>yet are at a</hi> leſſer <hi>diſtance from ſuch who claim ſo</hi>-little.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſecond Objection. Of the Juriſdiction over Particular Churches in Synods, Eccleſiaſtical Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> §. <hi>1.</hi> as exerciſed with us. §. <hi>2.</hi> and in other places.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. THere are <hi>Synods, Conſiſtories, Colloquies,</hi> and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts, which exerciſe an Authority in ſpiritual matters over Churches: Therefore that of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate before mentioned, is not ſo neceſſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is humbly denied, and aſſerted, That theſe greater Aſſemblies, a Synod, Claſſis, Coloquie, and the like, either have no ſuch coactive Juriſdiction, as we mentioned, or are dependent upon the Civil Magiſtrate for it. This we ſhall ſhew, by declaring more fully what Eccleſiaſtical Power is exerciſed by Synods, or ſuch Courts. 1. <hi>In this Kingdom.</hi> 2. <hi>In other Reformed Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Eccleſiaſtical Courts in this Kingdom are of two ſorts:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There are, we know, Spiritual Courts, (ſo termed) ſuch as the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> the <hi>Arches,</hi> Court of <hi>Faculties,</hi> the <hi>Archdeacons</hi> and <hi>Commiſſaries</hi> Courts: Theſe claim only from the Civil Powers, as was ſhewed before.<note place="margin">Pag. 45, 46.</note> In the Statute of 37 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 17. it is declared, <hi>That the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons, have no manner of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, but by, from, and under the King's Royal Majeſty.</hi> By the Statute alſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:63430:31"/>of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>All Courts Eccleſiaſtical within the Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>ought to be kept by no other Power or Authority either Foreign or within the Realm, but by the Authority of His moſt Excellent Majeſty.</hi> And it was further Enacted, <hi>That all their Proceſs ſhall iſſue out under the King's Seal, and His Name and Style, &amp;c.</hi> but ſince repealed. Dr. <hi>Coſens,</hi> in his learned Defence of them, and their Proceedings, aſſerts thus: <hi>They are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>warranted by the Statute and Canon Law of this Nation;</hi> profeſſing alſo, that there were Reaſon enough againſt thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Proceedings,<note place="margin">Apol. Part 1. Cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>if they were not claimed from the Crown, but from ſome other Authority immediately, as the Popiſh Clergy did theirs from, by the means and direction of the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Our <hi>Convocation</hi> or <hi>General Synod,</hi> which makes Laws and Canons about matters that are more ſpiritual. This is an ancient Court, and hath formerly been in <hi>it ſelf</hi> of great Authority in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Regulations; it's not ſo now, but <hi>dependent</hi> upon the Civil Magiſtrate, for whatſoever Juriſdiction or Coercive Power there exerciſed, which will appear in theſe Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are no <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Canons</hi> made by the Biſhops, and others of the Clergy in the Convocation,<note place="margin">Nihil habet vim legis pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſquam Regius aſſenſus fuerit adhibitus, iis quae Synodus decernanda cenſuerit. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins</hi> Polit. Ta. <hi>1.</hi> a.</note> that oblige under any Penalty, without the Stipulation and Aſſent of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, be it either in matters of Faith or Diſcipline. The 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Canons about them, concluded upon by the Synod in <hi>Anno</hi> 1562. engaged no man under any Penalty in our Law to believe, profeſs, or ſubſcribe, until they had an Aſſent or Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Civil Powers. Nor can they proceed againſt any Crime, as <hi>Hereſie, Apoſtaſie,</hi> or groſs Enormity in Doctrine, but what our Laws declare to be ſuch.</p>
               <p>And for matters of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> it appears by the Letters Patent, Copies whereof are annexed to the Canous pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>Anno</hi> 1603, and 1640. That 1. All power to <hi>meet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, treat, debate, and agree upon any matter for common good, is from ſuch Licence,</hi> Power and Authority <hi>as is</hi> granted <hi>to the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Chancellors, and other Members of the Convocation</hi> from His Majeſty <hi>of His ſpecial Grace, and by virtue of His Prerogative Royal and Supreme Authority in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes.</hi> And 2. the <hi>Synod</hi> having treated of, concluded and agreed upon <hi>Canons, Orders,</hi> &amp;c. To the end and purpoſe by His Majeſty limited and preſcribed unto them, they are to offer and preſent the ſame to His Majeſty in writing: <hi>He, upon mature conſideration taken thereupon,</hi> may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:63430:32"/>approve,<note place="margin">The Licence to the Convoc. in Anno 1640.</note> confirm, and ratifie, <hi>or otherwiſe</hi> diſallow, anihilate, <hi>and make void ſuch, and ſo many of the ſaid Canons, Orders,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as he ſhall think fit, requiſite, or convenient.</hi> And <hi>none of thoſe Canons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be of any</hi> force, <hi>effect, or validity</hi> in Law, <hi>but only ſuch, and ſo many of them, and after ſuch time as His Majeſty by His Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents ſhall approve and confirm the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Civil Magiſtrate may ſuſpend for what time he ſhall pleaſe, yea, wholly deprive any Biſhop or Biſhops from their Office and Place in this <hi>Synod,</hi> who are the chiefeſt Members thereof. He may Commiſſionate alſo by Writ<note n="*" place="margin">Cook Inſtit. pag. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note>, what other Perſons He ſhall pleaſe to ſit in Convocation with them. And if occaſion be, He may likewiſe wholly conſtitute another <hi>Syond,</hi> and nominate each particular Perſon of what Quality and of what Number of His Natives as He ſhall pleaſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Field,</hi> Of the Church. <hi>Lib. 5. cap. 53.</hi> Princeps poteſt aſſignare, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minare, &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quandocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; quamdiu ipſi placuerit hujuſmodi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digenis ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quos ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neos cenſuerit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>Coſin</hi> de Pol. Tab. <hi>1.</hi> a.</note> and give them like Authority in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical matters. So was that Synod of the 32. appointed (by <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and afterwards by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) to do the work of a Synod, and preſent a Body of Eccleſiaſtical Canons for Confirmation by the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe Laws, ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Ju. Ec. pag.</hi> 9. Dr. <hi>Ridley</hi>'s view. <hi>pag.</hi> 110. 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 19. 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Cook,</hi> are termed <hi>Regiae Leges Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticae,</hi> and another <hi>ſuch Eccleſiaſtical Laws as now are in force, are called</hi> the King's Eccleſiaſtical Laws, <hi>for that now all Juriſdiction, whether it be Temporal or Eccleſiaſtical, is the Kings.</hi> And if there be any thing difficult or doubtful in theſe Laws, the Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ultimately to be given in the Civil Judicatures. So <hi>Cook</hi>'s <hi>Inſtit. pag.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 74. To the King alſo is the laſt Appeal to be made, and <hi>Delegates</hi> appointed by Him, give final Determination in Controverſies, after adjudged by thoſe Laws and Canons in any, yea, the higheſt of thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Courts. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatio ſit ad Principem &amp; non extra Regnum,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Coſen,</hi> and tells us it is a Juriſdiction <hi>Coronae Regiae de Jure debita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The King's Majeſty may <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with any of thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> or Eccleſiaſtical Laws, indulge the Omiſſion of what is enjoined by them, make void the Crime, and remove the Penalty incurred by breach of them, yea, and give Faculty to do or practiſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, any Synodical Eſtabliſhment or long uſage to the contrary notwithſtanding, in what <hi>offends not the Holy Scripture and Laws of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The King may exempt Perſons and Societies from the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the <hi>Ordinary</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or any elſe who are to execute theſe Canons.<note place="margin">De Jure Eccleſ.</note> This my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> aſſerts, and as a Prerogative
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:63430:32"/>annexed to the Crown. He gives many Inſtances of ſuch <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations</hi> in ſeveral Kings Reigns, both ancient, and of later times. For doubtleſs what Power He grants, and is exerciſed under Him, may be re-aſſumed by Him. And Priviledge, even whole Pariſhes if he pleaſe, from <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Synodical</hi> Juriſdiction, and ſuch Pariſhes are ſaid to be <hi>Regiae Majeſtati immediate ſubditae:</hi> Mocket, <hi>de Eccleſiaſtica Ang. Pol. pag.</hi> 294. And many Pariſhes to this day, ſtand thus exempted, by the favour and grant of Princes formerly. The <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Churches in ſeveral Parts of this Kingdom, by Patent from <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. were exempted from the then Eſtabliſhment, and exerciſed a <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and Forms of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> according to their own Perſwaſion, our Synod and Eccleſiaſtical Courts having, by vertue of this Exemption, nothing to do with their Miniſters or Churches; which Priviledge hath been confirmed to them by our Kings that Reigned ſince, and are enjoined to this day, His Majeſty that now is, by His Prerogative in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, notwithſtanding the preſent Form of Worſhip and Ceremonies, Graciouſly indulged Tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a <hi>Forbearance</hi> in what they were not ſatisfied, and to practiſe otherwiſe, <hi>Declaration of</hi> October, 1660.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There is no matter or thing appertaining to Religion, or firſt Table-Duties, or ſo intimate and properly ſpiritual, which a Synod or Convocation hath Cogniſance of, and may make Laws and Canons about: But the like things have been eſtabliſhed by the Civil Powers (more than ſometimes for Advice) without it, as will abundantly appear in the many Statutes and Laws of former and later Times, as againſt <hi>Swearing, Perjury, Sabbath-breaking,</hi> &amp;c. That one inſtance, the <hi>Liturgy, and ordering Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> the many Rubricks in each of thoſe Books, are ſo many Canons and Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitutions, inſomuch as ſome have termed the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> Synods, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> obſerving alſo, that in the King's Writ, by which a Parliament is called, there is expreſly committed unto them the Conſiderations of what concerneth the <hi>Church</hi> as the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There hath been alſo <hi>Injunctions, Declarations, Advertiſements, Proclamations,</hi> and the like Edicts publiſhed in Eccleſiaſtical Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:63430:33"/>from time to time by our Princes, without calling or adviſing with a Synod: And Obedience hath been required unto thoſe <hi>Precepts,</hi> by the Ordinary in each Dioceſs, as well as to the <hi>Canons</hi> and Eccleſiaſtical Laws made by Synods.</p>
               <p>The Dependency therefore of Synods and Convocations upon the Civil Magiſtrate, according to the Conſtitution and Practice here in <hi>England,</hi> is very great and apparent: For,
<list>
                     <item>I. They can make no Canon, or Eccleſiaſtical Law, without the Civil Magiſtrate, but he can and may without them.</item>
                     <item>II.<note place="margin">His Majeſties Licence to the Convocation, <hi>May 12. 1640.</hi>
                        </note> None of their Laws, though ever ſo Ancient, but may be revoked by a Parliament; but the Rubricks, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Laws eſtabliſhed by it, may not be medled with by the Convocation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude with B. <hi>Bilſon,</hi> who ſeems to ſtate the Nature and Occaſion of Synods, as they are in this Kingdom, very fully, and indeed much as they ought to be whereſoever they are called; his words are theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>With us no Synods may aſſemble without the Prince's War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,<note place="margin">D. <hi>Bilſ.</hi> Per. Gov. cap. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>383.</hi>
                     </note> as well to meet as to conſult of any matter touching the ſtate of this Realm: And why? They be no Court <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the Prince, nor <hi>ſuperior</hi> to the Prince, but ſubjected in all things to the Prince, and appointed by the Laws of God and man, in Truth and Godlineſs, to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> and <hi>direct</hi> the Prince when and where they ſhall be called to aſſemble; otherwiſe they have no power of themſelves to make <hi>Decrees,</hi> when there is a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, neither may they challenge the judicial hearing or ending of Eccleſiaſtical Controverſies <hi>without</hi> or againſt the Prince's liking.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It appears evidently hereby, that in the Judgment of the Learned Author, Synods, in their Nature and Uſe, are not for <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> where there is a Chriſtian Magiſtrate; or otherwiſe than as Aſſiſtants only to counſel and adviſe Him.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:63430:33"/>
               <p>THe Synods in <hi>other Reformed Churches</hi> claim a <hi>coercive</hi> Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,<note place="margin">Diſcip. of <hi>Scot.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> alſo Act. of G. Aſſemb. before the Confeſ. of Faith. Jus divinum regiminis, cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> from an <hi>intrinſick</hi> right received immediatly from Jeſus Chriſt, as Miniſters of the Goſpel. There being no expreſs Scriptures to uphold this Aſſertion, and the light of Nature and common reaſon being ſuppoſed ſufficient to create a <hi>jus divinum.</hi> The Authors of this perſwaſion argue thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>In all Kingdoms and Republicks, if wrong be done by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Courts, we may have right by appealing to a Court ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior in Authority; there ought therefore to be ſuch an order in Churches, that is, a Claſſis, Synod, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That there may be regular Appeals in like Caſes. And further they argue,<note place="margin">Jus D. regim. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> if it be not ſo, when whole Churches or their Conſiſtories tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, there is no ordinary Remedy.<note place="margin">Aſſembly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute p. <hi>114.</hi>
                     </note> The Proviſion Chriſt hath made for Government in his Church will be found de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective: For though there be a Remedy for particular perſons;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rutherſ.</hi> peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Plea, cap. <hi>15.</hi> Aſſertion of the Gover. of <hi>Scot.</hi> by <hi>G. Gilleſpie</hi> part <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4</hi>
                     </note> yet for a Church offending, there is none, if there be not a ſuperior Church or Eccleſiaſtical Power to appeal unto.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Leaving wholly what they pretend from Scriptures: I ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this only their Reaſoning from common light, it being more ſuitable to our preſent ſubject; and in the general ſay.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 1. In the Myſteries of the Goſpel (from which by their own conceſſions, Church-communion and Diſcipline is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded any more than Preaching or the Sacraments) It is very unſafe to make the dim Eye of Reaſon our Guide. Of what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage ſuch ſuppoſitions have been, in producing <hi>Arminianiſm, Socinianiſm, Platoniſm,</hi> &amp;c. but eſpecially of the many groſs Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and loathſom Superſtitions in Popiſh Worſhip: we cannot be ignorant.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> 2. An Appeal (as underſtood in this diſpute, and ordinarily by <hi>Civilians</hi>) is <hi>a provocation to a ſuperior Tribunal, upon the error or wrong done by an Inferior.</hi> Such an Appeal is not eſſential to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, unleſs we can ſuppoſe a <hi>progreſſus in infinitum:</hi> Nor is there a defect in that Government where it cannot be had. Some Societies are 1. So <hi>low</hi> and little in compaſs, as they need not ſuch Appeals. A Family is a compleat Society or Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though there be not a Superior in the ſame kind, that is, an Economical power to appeal unto; ſo may a Church be, though not a Superior in a <hi>ſeries,</hi> properly Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical. 2. Others ſo <hi>High.</hi> If there be an Error or Wrong done in or by a general Aſſembly or National Synod, (ſuppoſed in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:63430:34"/>of power of greateſt perfection) we have no remedy,<note place="margin">Argued by the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland, Anno 41.</hi> p. <hi>1, 2, 9.</hi> Alſo their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Croſs Petition. <hi>P. 10.</hi>
                  </note> no Superior to appeal unto; therefore they term their Church or General Aſſembly an <hi>Independent.</hi> If it be ſaid, as it is by ſome, we may appeal from it to an <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Councel. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe great Councels have erred, and may, and what then is the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or further Proviſion? To what Eccleſiaſtical Tribunal Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior can we appeal from them?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> To anſwer more particularly: This Reaſoning being grounded upon a Similitude betwixt the Miniſterial Government of Chriſt, and the Political Government of Kingdoms, we ſay there is not <hi>Par ratio,</hi> and therefore no juſt conſequence. The Diſparity will appear in divers Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſparity. </seg>I</label> In their Natures, as <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> Aſſemblies. In this the Difference is ſo great as <hi>Councels, Schoolmen,</hi> and <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> who all grant Appeals in Civil Affairs: yet in Eccleſiaſtical Matters the ordinary uſe of them is ſo conſtantly and generally denied,<note place="margin">Videtur axio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma communiter acceptum inter probos Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos Appellatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vocem au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendam non eſſe, <hi>Suar.</hi> de virt. Tom. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>99.</hi>
                  </note> as it is an Axiom, ſaith One, <hi>That in Religious Cauſes, the Voice of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing is not to be heard or mentioned.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter he gives us the Reaſons of it in theſe words: <hi>Si in ordinariis cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionibus quae juxta diſciplinam religioſam fiunt, locum haberet Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatio à Priore ad Provincialem, &amp; à Provinciali ad Generalem; magna ſequeretur perturbatio, &amp; diſciplina religioſa ſine dubio corrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> &amp;c. <q>In ordinary Cenſures, and ſuch as are according to a Religious Diſcipline, if Appeals ſhould be made from the Prior to the Provincial, and from the Provincial to the General, it would breed a great Diſturbance, and be doubtleſs the Ruine of Religious Diſcipline: For, 1. Inferiour Governours would quickly be deſpiſed, and have little Reverence or Fear. 2. By ſuch a dilatory way, opportunity will be given by Friends, or under-hand working, to prevent any Religious Diſcipline. It is therefore expedient for the good of Religion, that there be a more ſimple way of procedure in theſe ſpiritual Corrections, and that it be without any kind of Appellation:</q> Thus far <hi>Suarez.</hi> And others of them alſo tell us, That in a <hi>voluntary</hi> and <hi>brotherly Society,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Soto</hi> de Juſt. lib. <hi>54.6.</hi> art.</note> it's more comely and honourable to end Offences and Differences in a private and peaceable way, amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and within the Society, than by clamorous Appeals, to make Matters more publick. It ſhould not be of little weight alſo with us, the Tenderneſs of Chriſt, if it be confidered, and how he would not have Breaches and Offences amongſt Brethren
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:63430:34"/>to be made more publick, or carried further than is neceſſary. And by any thing we find in the Text, there is no Neceſſity we ſhould carry Matters for Cenſure, out of the Church where the Offence is; if there were, doubtleſs Chriſt would have given us direction as well for the managing of Appeals FROM a Church, as IN a Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. where each ſtep and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, in the progreſs from a leſſer to a greater Authority, is deſcribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſparity. </seg>II</label> From the different condition of <hi>Puniſhments</hi> in reſpect to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, if unjuſtly inflicted. Church-Cenſures have little operation on us, further than our own Conſcience and the Spirit of Chriſt make them effectual, by working them in upon us: But if inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where no juſt Cauſe, and <hi>Clave errante,</hi> the Spirit of Chriſt will not convince us of Sin, or let in Satan's Terrors, nor any ſuch impreſſions of Grief or Shame as much to afflict us being inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. How little hath the <hi>Pope's Bulls,</hi> or ſuch Thundrings from <hi>Rome,</hi> been valued or eſteemed; or Excommunications ſent out of our <hi>Spiritual Courts,</hi> when we know it is but for a <hi>Four-penny</hi> Offence? In Civil Affairs it is much otherwiſe: For, be the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>juſt</hi> or <hi>unjuſt,</hi> the Execution of it is equally <hi>grievous,</hi> and a puniſhment, be it in reſpect of Life, Liberty, or Eſtate; and there is no way either to avoid or mitigate ſuch wrongs, but by Appeals: The neceſſity of ſuch Appeals therefore is very great, but in reſpect to Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, little or nothing at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſparity. </seg>III</label> The ordinary <hi>end</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> of Appeals, is either, 1. For Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of Perſons ſuffering: Or, 2. That corrupt Judges be cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and unjuſt Sentences reſcinded. Perſons come to be relieved, when by Appeals to Higher Powers there is a better underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either 1. in the Rule and Law; or, 2. a more righteous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters of Fact. There are none of theſe Ends or Uſes of an Appeal ſo accompliſhable in an Eccleſiaſtical Proceſs, as in a Civil.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the <hi>Rule</hi> be obſcure, a right underſtanding of it may <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly</hi> be had by appealing in <hi>Civil</hi> Affairs; the Supreme Court is here on Earth, that made the Rule or Law; what's determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a Parliament, or ſuch Perſons as are intruſted by it to this purpoſe, is to us unqueſtionable.</p>
               <p>But it's otherwiſe in <hi>Church</hi> Affairs, our Law-giver is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and cannot in ſuch a forenſical way be appealed unto, nor hath he left any Vicar or Viſible Judge under him, of greater Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:63430:35"/>in reſpect of Infallibility, than a particular Church, <hi>which is the ground and pillar of truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſome of them in great and weighty matters (not otherwiſe) that are ſpiritual, yield Appeals; but it's upon this Suppoſition, that the Cauſe, at laſt, will be brought to a Tribunal that is Infallible, <hi>Licitumeſt</hi> (ſaith P. de Aragon) <hi>in re grave cuique cauſam ſuam defferre ad ſedem Apoſtolicam;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aragon, <hi>in</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 69. <hi>a.</hi> 3. <hi>D. Th.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quando vel ex imperitia, vel ex Paſſione inferiorum judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum qui</hi> homines <hi>ſunt ac</hi> decipi <hi>poſſunt, injuriam patitur:</hi> The Pope cannot be deceived, he is more than a Man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Matters of Fact, by reaſon of Appeals, come to be ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at a great diſtance from the place where the Crime and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence lieth, which in Worldly Concernments may with more Righteouſneſs be done, than in what is Spiritual, and of Church Cognizance.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Tranſgreſſions come under a Civil Judgment, as materially conſidered, and according to the groſs Act, but brought to the Church, not as <hi>Sins</hi> ſimple, but as <hi>Scandals</hi> and Offences, which is a Conſideration not ſo obvious, but requires good judgment in the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> as well as in the Judges. The <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> alſo, or <hi>Penitency</hi> of the Perſon offending, accordingly as Teſtimony ſhall be given of either, is a more difficult matter to make out, than either the <hi>Sin</hi> it ſelf, or the <hi>Scandal.</hi> Repentance, Godly Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or the contrary, is the principal thing to be regarded in Church-proceſs. Repentance, I ſay, in truth and ſincerity, ſo far as we can judge in (a ſeeing and not blind) charity. It is not only the Paſſion, Sorrow, or Shame, but <hi>Godly Sorrow,</hi> which is more ſpiritual, and deeper in the heart, and requireth much and particular knowledge of the Perſon, and his temper, and ſuch as cannot be attained at a diſtance, but by frequent and familiar Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. To ſit in the Stool of Repentance, ſtand in a White Sheet, or do <hi>Penance,</hi> (as it's termed) theſe are (as <hi>the fruits of the fleſh</hi>) <hi>manifeſt,</hi> and judged of at the greateſt diſtance, it's not ſo deep,<note place="margin">Prov. 20.5.</note> as we need much <hi>underſtanding</hi> to <hi>draw it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Cenſure, whether binding or looſing, is to be executed always by the particular Church where the Offender is a Member; thoſe perſons, above all others, are to have a particular knowledge of his Crime and true Repentance; they are <hi>to forgive, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their love,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.7. Mat. 18.15, 17</note> or otherwiſe, to <hi>withdraw</hi> from him. <hi>If THY Brother offend thee, let him be unto THEE an Heathen,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Execution</hi> of the Cenſure being by each Brother of that Church,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:63430:35"/>it is neceſſary the <hi>Examination</hi> of the matter be before them. Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Duties are not to be performed upon an <hi>implicit</hi> Faith. What knowledge, but by remote hereſay, can a Church in the <hi>Orchades</hi> have of a mans repentance or obſtinacy, the ultimate tryal and cognizance whereof, is taken by a Synod at <hi>Edenhurgh.</hi> Civil cenſures are for Satisfaction of the whole Nation, and not the Pariſh or Borough only where the crime was committed: but in a Church-cenſure, the particular Aſſembly being only, and no other Congregation, or perſon morally <hi>leavened,</hi> and charged with the offence, are principally, and in the firſt place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, to have ſatisfaction of the repentance and ſubmiſſion of the perſon offending: For by this means only their <hi>Lump</hi> or Church, becomes again <hi>unleavened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diſparity. </seg>4</label> 4. The other <hi>End</hi> (before mentioned) and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Appeals is, that our <hi>Judges</hi> and their <hi>Sentence</hi> be cenſured and judged by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Tribunals. To which proceeding,<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>naequa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> res per quaſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> res naſcitur per eaſdem diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitur.</note> the Judges in Civil Judicatures are liable; but there is not the like Subordination in Churches for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the Power and Authority placed in their Inferior Courts, is no other but the influx of the ſupream Civil Powers, to whom we always make our laſt Appeal, and therefore proper to them, to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> Actings, nay utterly to <hi>deſtroy</hi> in part or in whole, what Jurisdiction is derived from them, as appears in the Conſtitution of all Kingdoms: But it is not ſo here a particular Church. The Court we are to Appeal from, hath not its Being or Jurisdiction, from a Claſſis or Synod;<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſia Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochialis eſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia vera eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentialiter &amp; integraliter abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ulla cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondentia vel Synodo Voet. de Syn. pag. <hi>13. Parker</hi> de Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> It is an autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching of an obſtinate Church we plead for. <hi>Ruth.</hi> peaceable Plea, cap. <hi>15.</hi> p. <hi>223,</hi> and p. <hi>222.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication is an authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching.</note> theſe rather derive their Power from it, being <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> only, as our Brethren have formerly written. Particular Churches, they term <hi>Eccleſiae primae,</hi> and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods <hi>Eccleſiae ortae.</hi> Again, if Synods (as they grant) exerciſe over Churches a Power only <hi>cumulative,</hi> not <hi>deſtructive:</hi> How can they Excommunicate a Church, ſeeing Excommunication ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a Society as <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> which is to unchurch them, as Mr. <hi>Rutherford</hi> rightly affirms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Although whole Churches may be puniſhed for male Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration by the <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrate, yet may not an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Power meerly ſuch, do the like, for to deſtroy or ſave whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, for the Evil of a major part, or a few perſons, is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the Lord himſelf, which he communicates alſo in ſome caſes to Civil Magiſtrates, his <hi>Deputies,</hi> but in no caſe to Churches; it being an Authority high and Princely, and not at
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:63430:36"/>all ſutable to ſuch as have only a Miniſtry, and not a Dominion. Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> tells us, That <hi>a Cenſure is not to be drawn on the whole Body of the Church;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Brotherly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>102.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for as the Laws forbid to Excommunicate a Society or Corporation, becauſe it may happen, that thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent may be intangled in the cenſure: So Right and Religion forbids to exclude whole Churches from the Communion of the Faithful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this cannot be done without an injury and contempt to many that be innocent.</hi> What ever formerly of this ſame unchurching power in Synods hath been aſſerted, yet ſince upon further debate we are told; this ſame <hi>Excommunieating of whole Churches is a thing not known in the</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Government, and not the Churches, but particular perſons in the Churches are cenſured.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſſemb. diſputes pag. <hi>180.</hi>
                  </note> But how can we ſay ſingle perſons only are to be cenſured, and not the whole Church? Whenas we know the <hi>contending parties</hi> of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoever, are both equally liable to the <hi>Cenſure of the Judge.</hi> Now when matters are brought by Appeal to a ſuperior Court, the Court Appealed from, is a Party; and in this reſpect upon no higher terms than the <hi>pars appellans,</hi> though a ſingle perſon.</p>
               <p>But grant it be ſo, and that the object of a Cenſure from a Synod be only particular members.<note place="margin">Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ejus<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatio poſt appellationem legitimam la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, eſt nulla. <hi>Nardus</hi> p. <hi>53.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> Then, 1. Churches cannot have ſuch a remedy as in Civil States; for Appeals of this Nature are not to be made to any, but perſons inveſted with ſuch a power, as may ſuſpend, or make void in part, or in whole, the power of that Court by whom the wrong hath been done and Appealed from, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there be no Power in a Synod, of ſuch a proportion ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to a Church, as to cenſure it by Excommunication or Suſpenſion at leaſt: Then will the Members of this Church, by admitting ſuch Appeals, be neceſſarily under a twofold Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction not ſubordinate, which tends to the greateſt confuſion imaginable: For if the Synod and the Church in their Light and Apprehenſions vary about the condition of an Offender, one of them may in Conſcience be bound to juſtify whom the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is no <hi>ſupply</hi> of a ſuppoſed <hi>Defect,</hi> or Addition of what was not before, for if their ſuperior powers Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate particular Members only and not the whole Church: This is nothing more than each particular Church hath power to do. And it is as much an Ordinance of Chriſt, where two or three,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:63430:36"/>that is a leſſer number are gathered together, as where a greater; a Cenſure by the Church at <hi>Keneria,</hi> is as much a Cenſure, as if by <hi>Corinth.</hi> If a Quarter Seſſions Execute a man, its as much a Judicial deal, as if judged by the Aſſize, <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. The reaſon is obvious, its the Law that judges him, not this or that Judicature: So it is the Law and appointment of Chriſt that Excommunicates, not this or that Presbytery, greater or leſs, and this Law is the ſame to all.</p>
               <p>We come now to the other part of the Argument, drawn from the light of Nature, <hi>If Appeals be not, there will be a defect in Chriſt's Government; Perſons are left without remedy, for wrongs done by whole Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer with <hi>Suarez</hi> in the ſame caſe,<note place="margin">De virtute <hi>Tom. 4.</hi> p. <hi>99.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Argumentum eſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ab ſpecie ad genus negativum, defenſio eſt genus &amp; latius patet quam appellatio. Poteſt enim ad ſuperiorem recurrere per ſimplicene quaerelam vel per modum ſupplicationis, &amp;c. quod eſt ſufficens remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um diverſum appellatione &amp; multo magis decens religioſum ſtatum.</hi> 
                  <q>It is an Argument from the <hi>Species</hi> to the <hi>Genus,</hi> there are other ways of defence. We may have recourſe to a Superior by ſimple <hi>Complaint,</hi> or by way of <hi>Supplication;</hi> which is a ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and divers from an <hi>Appellation,</hi> and much more becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtate of Religion; thus that Author.</q> More particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we therefore Anſwer.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>There may be a ſufficient defence or remedy, though not by Appeals.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>There may be Appeals, though not in ſuch a way.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. For the firſt, this Addreſs or <hi>Recurſus</hi> to others Superior or equal, is not for the putting forth any Act of Juriſdiction or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion: Such perſons interpoſe by way of Intreaty, Perſwaſion, Pleading the Cauſe of the wronged, Reproving, Threathing, or in ſuch way, as a ſingle Paſtor may deal with any of his people. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> often, in a difference between <hi>Philemon</hi> and <hi>Oneſimus, Philem.</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>I beſeech thee for</hi> Oneſimus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>I beſeech</hi> Evo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias <hi>and</hi> Syntiche: It was upon ſome breach in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren that there be no Diviſion.</hi> This inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Apoſtle with the <hi>Corinths,</hi> was upon the deſire of the <hi>Houſe of Cloe</hi> ver. 11. There may alſo be more earneſt <hi>Pleadings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Reaſonings, Rebukes;</hi> yea openly, and before others.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11, 14.</note> The Apoſtles were equal in Authority, yet <hi>Paul.</hi> did not only Reaſon and Plead with <hi>Peter,</hi> but Rebuke and Reprove him publickly, and before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:63430:37"/>And in his dealing with <hi>Barnabas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 15.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit did riſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and yet no Power or Juriſdiction exerciſed, or might be by one Apoſtle over another.</p>
               <p>If Synods be applyed unto, only for Counſel and advice in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and difficult caſes, it is a <hi>proviſion</hi> not to be deſpiſed. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-light in an inſtruction or reproof is cogent, by what hand ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever adminiſtred, but more eſpecially when in the way of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance or Appointment of Chriſt. As are Paſtors, and Synods, though intruſted with a <hi>Declarative</hi> Authority only.</p>
               <p>Let it be conſider'd how the greateſt reformation made in the Hearts and Lives of men and women, is ordinarily by the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Word of God in the Ordinance of Preaching; which is the Inſtruction, Reproofs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a ſingle Miniſter, who hath not power to Excommunicate ſuch as deſpiſe his Doctrine. <hi>Faith comes by Hearing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> not by Diſcipline. Until they be judged, believers they <hi>are without.</hi> If this means, or ſuch a Doctrinal Application by a ſingle Miniſter, be ſufficient to make ſuch Reformation upon ſingle perſons, and thoſe that as yet own not Chriſt, or have Conſcience of an Ordinance, why ſhould we not expect the like fruit where many Miniſters are Synodically gathered for the Reformation of whole Churches, (perſons profeſſing to underſtand and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſo ſolemn an Ordinance of Chriſt) though there be no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive Power intruſted with it, to enforce Submiſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Receptum eſt in Gallia ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticis poſſe provocari ad ad curias ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premas Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum <hi>P. Gr. Tholoſ.</hi> l. <hi>50.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> §. <hi>36. Ruther.</hi> Due Right cap. <hi>6. §. 5.</hi> pag. <hi>396.</hi>
                  </note> There <hi>may be Appeals, though not in the ſame Series,</hi> but to a Tribunal extrinſecal, and not meerly Spiritual: as when we appeal to the Civil Magiſtrate, or ſuch as are appointed by him over Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical matters. For 1. if <hi>the King in his Laws, and the Church in their Synodical Canons, command and forbid one and the ſame things,</hi> as is aſſerted. And 2. if the perſons commanded ſtand as much in a Civil Relation to their Prince, being Subjects, as they do in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Relation to the Church, as Members. Doubtleſs the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrate having a Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical matters as in Civil, and (eſpecially) being aſſiſted by the <hi>Councel</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> of Synods, is a ſufficient and effectual means to reform the miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of particular Churches, if appealed unto.</p>
               <p>The truth is, though Churches were threatned, or ſtruck with the higheſt cenſures (being meerly Spiritual) and from a National Synod the higheſt Throne: Were it not from foreſight, that if ſuch Diſcipline be deſpiſed, the Magiſtrates Sword, by ſome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:63430:37"/>puniſhment will ſecond it, there would be little fear or dread of thoſe Synodical cenſures. And if ſo, as it is apparent to the moſt in a National or Provincial Church as ordinarily conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, it is no otherwiſe. Common Reaſon will direct us ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to go <hi>immediatly</hi> by <hi>Appeals</hi> to the Civil Magiſtrate, or his Delegates, than in ſuch a compaſs, as to drive the cauſe from a Conſiſtory to a Claſſis, from thence to a Provincial Synod, and after that to a National Aſſembly; and when all this is done, there is little to any purpoſe done, if not ſeconded by a <hi>ſecular arm.</hi> Hence our learned Brethren formerly admitted no other Appeals of this nature, but to the Civil Magiſtrate, as we have fully ſhewed in the former <hi>Digreſſion:</hi> To which we add what is by that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor further ſaid. <q>If the Brethren or Officers in a Church be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> and will not hearken to Reaſon, they (that are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) are to crave the aſſiſtance of the Civil Magiſtrate, who alone hath Power, and who ought by the Civil Sword and Authority, procure to all Members of the Church, Governors or others, freedom from all manifeſt injuries and wrongs.</q> The manner how the Civil Magiſtrate is to proceed in Church-cauſes, is there alſo deſcribed to us in the words following; <q>Though the Civil Magiſtrate cannot abſolve the Excommunicate perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or take away this power from the Church, yet when they or any of them ſhall apparently abuſe the ſame, he is bound by the Law of God, and by virtue of his Office grounded upon the ſame, to puniſh them ſeverely for it, and to force them by Civil Mulcts to rectiſy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>THus I have done with that firſt Conſideration, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whereof the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Eccleſiaſtical power is affirmed: Which is, in reſpect to the well-being of <hi>Churches.</hi> There is another conſideration re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining now likewiſe to be proſecuted, ſhewing the like neceſſity of this Power, in reſpect and relation to the well-being of the <hi>Commonwealth.</hi> The <hi>Knowledge</hi> and true <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, and the means hereof the <hi>word</hi> of God, is a national gift. <hi>He hath given his Law to</hi> Jacob — <hi>he hath not dealt ſo with other Nations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>147.</hi>
                  </note> It was true then, for <hi>Iſrael</hi> had this priviledge as a peculiar; but now it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And where the Lord is ſo bountiful to a Nation, thus to give the means of Life and Salvation, it is a <hi>Depoſitum</hi> Governors muſt account for. The whole Nation becomes peaceable, proſperous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:63430:38"/>or otherwiſe, according as the matters of God and his Worſhip, are more or leſs Religiouſly attended by the Governors and People thereof. This Conſideration is urged by Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Daven. de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du cont. ca. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>91.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Regis poteſtas judiciaria ſe extendit ad ea omnia ſancienda quae rem publicam florentem conſervant at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad ea tollenda,</hi> &amp;c. <q>The Kings Legiſlative power extends to the eſtabliſhming of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may preſerve a Commonwealth in a flouriſhing State, and the taking away of all ſuch things as may prejudice or ruine it. But the Religious Worſhip of God is granted of all, even of the very Heathens; as of concernment to the well-being of the Republick, and the neglect of it to the everſion of it.</q> The care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and orderly management of Religious affairs, being a ſpecial means and way to make the Republick proſperous, the care where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lieth upon the Magiſtrate: It is neceſſary that he both judge of, and put forth his Authority, in the procuring and preſerving ſuch a means or conducement, the further proſecution of this ſecond Argument, together with other particulars, requiſite to the reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this <hi>Caſe,</hi> I ſhall leave to a ſecond <hi>Part</hi> of this Diſcourſe, in which, after the clearing and vindicating the former part of the Oath as lawfully to be taken: The two great doubts ariſing from the latter part of it, ſhall more largely be inſiſted upon. The words are theſe: <hi>I ſhall to my Power Aſſiſt and Defend all Juriſdictions — belonging to the Kings Highneſs — or united to the Crown,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Doubts</hi> hereupon are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Juriſdiction, Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> granted and united to the Imperial Crown, are unknown unto us, and ſome of them Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted: How can we <hi>ſwear in judgment?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.2.</note> Anſw. Though there be not a diſtinct knowledge in reſpect of each particular, yet an Oath may be taken in Judgment, and how.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are ſome <hi>Juriſdictions, Priviledges,</hi> &amp;c. in Spiritual matters granted and united to the Crown, the lawfulneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ſcrupled; and we may poſſibly believe they do not <hi>belong</hi> to the <hi>Civil</hi> Magiſtrate, How can we ſwear to aſſiſt and defend him in ſuch, and <hi>Swear in Righteouſneſs? Anſw.</hi> In a Federacy, or Allegiance, to aſſiſt and defend another, againſt a common Enemy, if the things be juſt and lawful in <hi>His</hi> opinion, though doubted of, or thought otherwiſe in <hi>ours:</hi> It is no unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in us to give aſſiſtance according to our Oath. Theſe Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and Aſſertions I doubt not, will be made evident, in what is to follow, and be the other part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:63430:38"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>HAving ſatisfied divers Friends that were ſcrupled about the Oath of Supremacy, I was deſired by my Brethren in the Miniſtry, and others, (knowing my unhappy leiſure) to publiſh ſomething this way, wherein accordingly I made entrance, but finding this <hi>Oath</hi> not ſo much preſſed, and the <hi>Subject</hi> ſuch as is capable (from me eſpecially) of a various reception, I laid it long aſide, with purpoſe to make no further progreſs; afterwards underſtanding ſome Perſons of Honour judged ſuch a Work to be uſeful and ſeaſonable, it was re-aſſumed.</p>
               <p>In the Proſecution hereof, I have ſtated ſomething of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, as claimed by <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Churchmen</hi> of each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and how it ſtands in habitude and relation to His Majeſties <hi>Supremacy</hi> in theſe Affairs. Not with any purpoſe to reflect upon the judgment or practice of others, whom for their Learning and Holineſs I ſhall ever greatly reverence; but that I might the more fully and diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lay down what is aſſerted by thoſe of the Congregational way: And upon theſe Conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> It being now a ſeaſon for us, humbly to apply for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of our <hi>Conſciences</hi> in the Worſhip and Service of God, upon the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of His Majeſties moſt Gracious <hi>Declaration,</hi> exhibited on that behalf, wherein we underſtand our ſelves to be fully comprehended. And finding our Way and Principles, repreſented by ſome in Print, (though we fully agree with this, and other Reformed Churches, in all the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion,</hi> concerning the true Chriſtian Faith and <hi>Doctrine of Sacraments,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Printed Anno <hi>1658.</hi>
                  </note> which is evident by our Confeſſion of Faith) as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent</hi> with, and <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the Peace of Civil Government. This, if believed, cannot but be a ſufficient Block in the way of our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; I thought it neceſſary, for the removing all Prejudices in order to the obtaining of our aforeſaid Liberty, to give ſome further account of our <hi>Way,</hi> and to repreſent more diſtinctly and particularly our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; that it may appear, whatſoever hath been ſaid to the contrary, that there is nothing in them, but what is <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with, and moſt <hi>agreeable</hi> to the Civil Government; or that ſhould render us in any ſort uncapable of receiving the fruit and benefit of the King's Majeſties Favor and Indulgence promiſed to Tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> We find Eccleſiaſtical Power where claimed <hi>Jure Divino,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Secret. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Critoy.</hi>
                  </note> and immediately from the Lord, by their Churches or Officers, hath always been a matter of <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> as derogating from the King's Supremacy.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>I.</hi> The Juriſdiction we pretend to (as appears in this Diſcourſe)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:63430:39"/>and <hi>avouch</hi> as the appointment of Chriſt, is the <hi>loweſt</hi> for kind, and of <hi>narroweſt</hi> extention, exerciſed about the concernment only of a <hi>particular Congregation;</hi> and therefore we may well aſſert with that learned Biſhop,<note place="margin">B. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, pag. 24.</note> 
                  <q>It's very hard to give a ſatisfactory difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſuch an Eccleſiaſtical Power, and the Oeconomical (both claiming by Divine Right) why the one ſhould be more injurious to Regal Power than the other.</q> We can further ſay, the Power we claim is no other but ſuch alſo, as hath been always owned by our <hi>Laws</hi> and Writers of Note, to be immediately from God, and peculiar to his Holy Service, and the Sacred Function of the Miniſtery, with thoſe other Parochial Duties; as to <hi>Preach</hi> the Word, <hi>Adminiſter Sacraments,</hi> and the like: <hi>The word Sacraments, and the uſe of the Keys,</hi> (ſaith B. <hi>Bilſon</hi>) <hi>are things compriſed in the Church,</hi> (lie not open with other State-matters) <hi>and by God commanded to the Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, p. 170. &amp; 227. Againſt <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> p. 6. c. 9. D. 1, 2. Alſo D. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church, lib. 5. c. 53.</note> 
                  <hi>and are ſubject to no mortal Creature, Pope or Prince. We teach not Princes,</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi>) <hi>to offer up Incenſe or Sacrifice as</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah <hi>did, or to preach or adminiſter Sacraments, or to bind or to looſe.</hi> Each of theſe Duties are ſuch and ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, as our <hi>Princes openly</hi> and in their Laws diſown them, as not <hi>depending</hi> upon their <hi>Adminiſtration, or Authority.</hi> In the 37th. Article of the <hi>Engliſh Confeſſion,</hi> it is thus: <hi>We give not to our Princes the Miniſtring either of God's Word, or the Sacrament:</hi> And in the <hi>Admonition,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Kings and Queens of this Realm, Poſſeſſors of the Crown, challenge not Authority and Power of Miniſtery of Divine Offices in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Power or Juriſdiction exerciſed over theſe particular Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, or their Officers, hath its ſtation in a <hi>higher Region,</hi> and ſuch, as in which all Chriſtian Magiſtrates in the world judge themſelves <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed;</hi> and that what is done in this kind by any Perſon or Aſſembly, be by a Power <hi>derived</hi> from them, and <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to them. So our Law, <hi>27 H. 8. c. 17. The Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, and other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, have no manner of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but by, from, and under the King's Royal Majeſty.</hi> And in the Statute of <hi>1 Edw. 6. c. 2. All Courts Eccleſiaſtical within the Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>ought to be kept by no other Authority either Foreign, or IN THE REALM, but by the Authority of His moſt Excellent Majeſty.</hi> It is evident therefore, that thoſe Superior Powers (of what Form or Denomination ſoever they be) that are over theſe Congregations, have their motions in <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s walk: But the holy and ſpiritual Duties peculiar to particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:63430:39"/>are expreſly remitted to them and their Miniſters, as the <hi>things of God,</hi> and not of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Our ſituation is low, and quite beneath <hi>thoſe Orbs,</hi> wherein the tranſactions of a National concernment <hi>move,</hi> and are managed. How Religion and Reformation thrive in a Nation, and is encouraged by the Governors thereof, we have a ſence, and form our thoughts and moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual prayers and endeavors accordingly. We are engaged hereunto as Members of the Catholick Church, and particularly concerned in the welfare of our Native Countrey; otherwiſe our Principles are to keep within our Congregational Precinct, and not to give Laws, or exerciſe Power over others, or to engage our ſelves (unleſs thereunto by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity called) in more publick Affairs. Nor do we believe (as we have jointly profeſſed) <hi>there is Power given by Chriſt to any Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod or Eccleſiaſtical Aſſemblies to Excommunicate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Confeſſion of Faith, pag. 61. Sect. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>or by their Publick Edicts to threaten Excommunication, or other Church-Cenſures againſt Churches, Magiſtrates, or their People, upon any ſuch account.</hi> And therefore we may be freed from the jealouſie of being <hi>Troublers</hi> or <hi>Retarders</hi> of others, in the work of Reformation, or publick Settlement. Or were we (or could we be) ſo, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation not long ſince attempted, otherwiſe than by not joining to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what our Conſciences were not clear in; or in not putting our neck voluntarily into a <hi>Yoke</hi> we conceived was not <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and therefore would not be <hi>eaſie</hi> in the ſervice of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> We have been blamed more than once for this <hi>Surname</hi> INDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENDENT, (though a title not of our own choice) as an inſolent aſſuming.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad <hi>Buch.</hi> pag. 91.</note> 
                  <hi>Miror etiam viris piis</hi>—&amp;c. (ſaith <hi>Spanhemius</hi>) <hi>Truly I marvel that holy men (ſo I judge them though diſſenting from us) ſhould not themſelves be diſſatisfied with the very title, an</hi> Independent Church, <hi>which ſeems to me not to ſtand with the modeſty of Chriſtians.</hi> The defects of all men through the blindneſs of their minds, ſince the Fall, is ſo great and obvious, as no Perſon or Society can aſſume to it ſelf an INDEPENDENCY in this reſpect, without intollerable Pride, Independency in reſpect of Power only is another thing; <hi>Power</hi> ſimply and in it ſelf is no Virtue, though <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Prudence</hi> and <hi>Fortitude</hi> by which it is managed, are. Not to be in Power, is no Sin nor Moral Defect, more than not to be <hi>Rich,</hi> or in <hi>Honour.</hi> It is not ſo much the <hi>Praiſe,</hi> as the <hi>Charge</hi> of him that receiveth it, the honour and glory of him that can give it; of him only it hath its proportion, and doth not become greater or leſs from any worth or induſtry found in thoſe that receive it, as Moral Virtues do. Power
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:63430:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>doth not vary in its kind, though the wiſdom and ability to manage it, be greater or leſs in him that hath it: So that Power, whether <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi> or <hi>limited,</hi> whether <hi>dependent</hi> or <hi>independent,</hi> is a moſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable thing in its ſelf, to be proud of, or glory in. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>there be any virtue, if there be any praiſe,</hi> Phil. <hi>4.8.</hi> It is <hi>Virtue,</hi> not <hi>Power,</hi> we ſhould be ambitious of, being an excellency in it ſelf; and without it, Power will be but a lifting us up to our own deſtruction. Whatſoever Virtue or Gift is deſirable for the manage of that Power Chriſt hath intruſted us with, we further ſeek after in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting other Churches, and endeavour that all matters difficult, and of common concernment, may be proceeded in with joint conſent. We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly <hi>depend</hi> upon Synods for Counſel, which comes forth ordinarily from ſuch Aſſemblies, better digeſted, and in a more perfect maturation, their part being to adviſe and give Councel onely; for men will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſdy ſpend much time to untie a knot, if there be a knife at hand to out it.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> amongſt other Reflections, met with this, from the falſe Apoſtles, who gave him out in their reckoning, as one that made ſome carnal advantage the <hi>ſcope</hi> of his <hi>Opinions;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.2, 3.</note> with this hard meaſure we have met from firſt to laſt, I am therefore willing to leave ſome account in the hand of my Friends (being now aged, and near my period) of thoſe Principles that have long (through grace) kept me and others ſteady in this perſwaſion: Not only in and through theſe late Changes and Diſputings, but divers years before, and when no ſuch Encouragements were, (as are ſurmiſed to be our aim) but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle inſerts in the midſt of his Church-Diſputes, a whole Chapter in the praiſe of Charity, and tells us, <hi>in ſeeking our own,</hi> (for want hereof) we are <hi>eaſily provoked,</hi> and <hi>behave our ſelves unſeemly, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>13.</hi> and apt to <hi>think</hi> and ſurmiſe <hi>evil: As for me</hi> (to uſe <hi>David</hi>'s words) <hi>the Lord hath upheld me in mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</hi> The reflecting thoughts whereof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.12.</note> have been as the conſolation of God in my Soul, when I lay many days together by the Graves ſide; Providence hath brought me back into a troubleſom world, where with patience and perſeverance, through Chriſt, I ſhall wait until my Courſe be finiſhed, <hi>following peace with all men,</hi> in the way of <hi>holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>P. NYE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:63430:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
